<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons preached at Christ-Church in the city of Dublin, before the honourable the General Convenion of Ireland. The first on Prov.11.14 at the first meeting of the said convention, March 2. 1659. The second on Jude v.19. at a publique fast appointed by the said convention, March 9. 1659. By Sem Coxe, Minister of the gospel and pastor at St. Katherines in Dublin.</title>
            <author>Coxe, Sem.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80730</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6726</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1026_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208752</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867674</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867674</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119995</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80730)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119995)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 152:E1026[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons preached at Christ-Church in the city of Dublin, before the honourable the General Convenion of Ireland. The first on Prov.11.14 at the first meeting of the said convention, March 2. 1659. The second on Jude v.19. at a publique fast appointed by the said convention, March 9. 1659. By Sem Coxe, Minister of the gospel and pastor at St. Katherines in Dublin.</title>
                  <author>Coxe, Sem.</author>
                  <author>Ireland. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 61, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by VVilliam Bladen,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini, 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an order to print dated at head: March the 9. 1659; and signed by: Ma. Barry Clerk of the General convention of Ireland.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf contains a colophon: Dublin, imprinted by VVilliam Bladen, Anno Domini, 1660.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 31".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, Irish --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119995:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119995:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Two Sermons Preached at Chriſt-Church in the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> before the Honourable the General CONVENTION of IRELAND.</p>
            <p>The firſt on Prov. 11. 14.</p>
            <p>At the firſt meeting of the ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, <hi>March</hi> 2. 1659.</p>
            <p>The ſecond on Jude v. 19.</p>
            <p>At a publique Faſt appointed by the ſaid Convention, <hi>March</hi> 9. 1659.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Sem Coxe</hi> Miniſter of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel and Paſtor at St. <hi>Katherines</hi> in <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Printed by VVILLIAM BLADEN<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> 1660.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119995:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119995:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE HONOURABLE The General CONVENTION of</hi> Ireland.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Patriots,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our deſire (which I inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret in the nature of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand) hath cauſed me (contrary to mine own di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition and inclination) to appear in publique.</p>
            <p>I can behold nothing in theſe my poor Labours that may deſerve your acceptance, onely this I can ſay, That I have endeavoured in theſe two Sermons to diſcharge a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to God, to his Church, and to You in particular, in which I do and ſhall find com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            <p>It is no ſmall mercy, That plain preaching of ſeaſonable Truths (which was formerly
<pb facs="tcp:119995:3"/> stifled by Sectarian ſpirits) is now revived and countenanced through your Patronage; this will ſtand upon your account for good at the great day of the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant of the raſh cenſures of unſtable ſpirits that have paſſed upon me for preaching theſe Sermons, becauſe I have med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with their Diana; and I expect much more unfriendly dealing now they appear to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique view; but I ſhall ſay with the Poet,</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>—Hic murus aheneus eſto</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nil conſcire ſibi,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <p>I can ſpeak it in ſincerity, That I have not intended to beſpatter any mans perſon, but to ſet out the loathſomneſs which is in the Tenets of thoſe men that have ſtudied (under the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pretence of piety and Chriſtian Liberty) to enſlave theſe three nations of England, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Scotland, yea (and which is worſe) to unchurch them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119995:3"/>
            <p> It is now above thirty years ſince my reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and learned Tutor, Mr. <hi>Arthur Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſam</hi> (whoſe name and praiſe is yet freſh in the Church of God, being in his life time <hi>accepted of all the godly, though differing in judgment,</hi> as <hi>Fuller</hi> witneſſeth in his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of Britain, Cent. 17. Book <hi>11.)</hi> did fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently adviſe me (and others) to beware of ſeparation from the Church of England (which errour began then to be buſie in the land) aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring me, That Separation was likely to be the bane both of Church and State; (How pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick his words were, the wofull experience of diverſe years by paſt hath ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed us) And therefore, whilſt he ſuffered much trouble and reſtraint under the exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances of Prelacy, he acted both by preaching and writing againſt this bitter weed of Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; inſomuch as the learned Dr. <hi>VVillet</hi> (in his Epiſtle dedicatory to Chriſts College be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:119995:4"/> his harmony upon the firſt of Samuel) ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him, <hi>Schiſmaticorum (qui vulgò Browniſtae) malleum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What difference there is between the Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts formerly, and our Separatiſts now, I yet deſcern not, (both of them in words and deeds denying to hold communion with our Church) ſave onely that theſe later have put a fairer dreſs upon this Monſter, that it may appear more amiable.</p>
            <p>Being warned by this divine Oracle, moſt conſonant to Scripture, I have endeavoured (ever ſince the Lord counted me faithful put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me into the Miniſtry) to bear my weak teſtimony againſt this general errour of the time; both becauſe it is the fruitful mother of manifold Hereſies, depriving the Church of all means to ſuppreſs them; and alſo becauſe from this Church-ſeparation, hath proceeded State-ſeparation even to the depriving us of all our
<pb facs="tcp:119995:4"/> birth-privileges as ſubjects, if Gods mercy had not ſeaſonably interpoſed.</p>
            <p>Now God almighty direct you in thoſe great affairs that are before you; and help you in the ſtrength of his holy Spirit to contend earneſtly for the faith once committed to the Saints, both againſt ſchiſm and hereſy on the one hand, and alſo againſt all prophaneſs and ungodlineſs on the other hand, That ye may be called the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairers of the breach made in the Church of God, the reſtorers of paths to dwell in, that ſo at the laſt the kingdom of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt may be advanced in the power and purity of his Ordinances among us, and Ireland may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>Inſula Sanctorum.</hi> So ſtill ſhall pray</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours and the Churches Servant in the work of the Goſpel, <hi>SEM COXE.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>From my ſtudy in St. Thomas-ſtreet in <hi>Dublin</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:119995:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>March</hi> the 3. 1659.</head>
            <head>By the General Convention of Ireland.</head>
            <p>ORdered, That Sir <hi>Paul Davys,</hi> Sir <hi>Theophilus Jones,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Dud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley Loftus,</hi> be and are appointed a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee to return the thanks of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention to Mr. <hi>Coxe,</hi> for the Sermon preached by him before the Convention yeſterday, and to deſire Mr. <hi>Coxe</hi> to cauſe his Sermon to be printed; And it is alſo Ordered, That Mr. <hi>Coxe</hi> be deſired by the ſaid Committee to attend the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention every morning to pray with them before the Sitting.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Signed by Order, Ma. Barry</hi> Clerk of the General Convention of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119995:5"/>
            <head>The Firſt Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Proverbs 11. 14.</bibl>
               <q>Where no counſel is the people fall, but in the multitude of Counſellors there is ſafety.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Proverbs of Solomon the ſon of David, King of Iſrael, are uſually methodized un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der three heads, <hi>viz.</hi> His Ethicks, his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks, and his Oeconomicks.</p>
            <p>His Politicks contain the Doctrine of the Government of Kingdoms, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths. Wherein Solomon treateth of four ſorts of Perſons that compleat ſuch a Government, and make it happy; <hi>viz.</hi> 1 A King or ſupreme Governor; 2 Counſellors of State; 3 Nobles, Favorites or Courtiers; 4 Subjects. Where ſuch a Government is the people flouriſh, otherwiſe they cannot be happy.</p>
            <p>Our Text, and our preſent Occaſion, lead us to ſpeak concerning Counſellors and their counſels; of perſons that are called to conſult <hi>de arduis Reipublicae;</hi> upon which account ye (Noble Senators) are convened this day.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119995:6"/>
            <p> Concerning Counſellors, Solomon acquainteth us, 1. With the Neceſſity of them. 2. With their Qualifications. The firſt our Text ſpeaketh of wherein the ſecond will alſo be included. So we ſhall come to the words themſelves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Where no counſel is the people fall, but in the multitude of Counſellors there is ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this divine Sentence may have the deeper impreſſion upon our hearts, let us ſeriouſly conſider who hath delivered it. This ſhall be laid down in two particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Solomon (who wrote this golden ſentence) was the wiſeſt man in the world. The Holy Ghoſt informeth us, 1 King 4. 30, 31. That <hi>his wiſdom excelled the wiſdom of all the children of the Eaſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> (that is, of the Arabians or Chaldeans) <hi>and all the wiſdom of Egypt</hi> (which was very great, as appeareth by that commendation given to <hi>Moſes</hi> Acts 7. 22. that <hi>he was learned in all the wiſdom of the Egyptians) that he was wiſer than all men, than Ethan the Ezrahite, and Heman, and Chalcol, and Darda the ſons of Mahol.</hi> None that write of civil politie are to be compared with him. Now upon this very account his judgment is to be diligently harkened unto. A wiſe mans ſayings deſerve the heeding.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But there is more than this to be conſidered touching Solomon; for he wrote this Proverb (as he did many others) by inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt. He was but the Pen-man of that which the Spirit of God dictated to him. And therefore this (as all other Scripture) is <hi>written for our learning</hi> Rom. 15. 4. His judgment herein is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring and infallible, ſo as we may reſt upon it as an undoubted truth of God.</p>
            <p>The Wiſe man by direction from God acquainteth us in this Text with two things,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 With that unavoidable hurt and damage which befalleth a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple deſtitute of counſel. <hi>Where no counſel is the people fall.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 With that great proſperity and advantage that ariſeth to a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by good Counſellors and their counſels. <hi>But in the multitude of Counſellors there is ſafety.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The ruine and miſery that overtaketh a people for want of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel is called a <hi>falling.</hi> The word <hi>Naphal</hi> in the Original beareth a double ſignification. For there is a twofold falling.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119995:6"/> 1 There is a <hi>falling</hi> into ſin againſt God, and ſo by ſin from God. Hence it is that the giants ſpoken of Gen. 6. 4. are called <hi>Nephilim,</hi> as being Apoſtates, fallen from God by their impiety. Of this kind of fall it is that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh 1. Cor. 10. 12. <hi>Let him that thinketh he ſtandeth take heed leſt he fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 There is a <hi>falling</hi> under judgment for ſin committed againſt God. As is clear. Hoſ. 14. 1. <hi>O Iſrael return unto the Lord thy God, for thou haſt fallen by thine iniquity;</hi> that is, thy ſin hath plunged thee into miſery. So the word is taken Gen. 14. 10. <hi>The Kings of Sodom and Gomorrah fled, and fell there;</hi> that is to ſay, they were ſlain there.</p>
            <p>This Text will bear both theſe acceptations, <hi>Where there is no coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel the people fall</hi> both into ſin and miſery: but I take it in the later ſenſe eſpecially, <hi>they fall</hi> into utter ruine, into unſpeakable miſery.</p>
            <p>The benefit or advantage that cometh to a Nation or People by much counſel, is called <hi>Safety,</hi> which word originally compriſeth all manner of ſafety, both corporal and ſpiritual, both from ſin and miſery.</p>
            <p>There are two intire Propoſitions in the Text.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Where no counſel is the people fall.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>In the multitude of Counſellors there is ſafety.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The one of theſe Propoſitions illuſtrateth the other. <hi>No counſel,</hi> and a <hi>multitude of Counſellors</hi> are oppoſed, ſo likewiſe are <hi>falling</hi> and <hi>ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſhall comprehend both theſe under this one general Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Propoſition.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That the proſperity or adverſity of a people dependeth very much upon their counſellors and counſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know you will expect before I proceed to the handling of this truth, that I caution it to prevent miſtake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caution.</hi> It muſt always be acknowledged, and thankfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, That the Lord our God (who is wonderfull in working) hath the chiefhand in the proſperity or downfall of Nations.</p>
            <p>There is nothing that cometh to paſs without the Providence of God, that is it which diſpoſeth even in the leaſt matters; in the <hi>fall of a sparrow to the ground</hi> Matth. 10 29. in the growth and beauty of the flowers of the field Matth. 6. 28-30. and ſo in all other things
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119995:7"/> that ſeem to be of the leaſt concernment. Chriſtians muſt not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the maxim of the Heathens, <hi>Non vacat exiguis rebus adeſse Jovi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much more is the Lords hand viſibly ſeen in the adverſity or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of Kingdoms and Commonwealths. Whence it is that the Lord appropriateth this unto himſelf as the chief agent in it. Iſa. 47. 5. <hi>I form the light and create darkneſs: I make peace and create evil: I the Lord do all theſe things.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, I am the cauſe of all goodneſs and proſperity through my benignity, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by my juſtice I am author of afflictions, puniſhments and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; for ſo we are to underſtand <hi>evil</hi> here; the evil of puniſhment and not the evil of ſin; for of that God cannot be the author. So likewiſe the Lord ſpeaketh again Jer. 18. 7. <hi>At what inſtant I ſhall speak concerning a nation and concerning a kingdom to pluck up, and pull down, and to deſtroy it.</hi> And Verſe 9. <hi>At what inſtant I ſhall speak concerning a nation and concerning a kingdom to build and, to plant it.</hi> The Lord (you ſee) aſcribeth both theſe to himſelf. So that the Providence of God is determined by no cauſe, but deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineth all cauſes, being the univerſal and particular cauſe of all things.</p>
            <p>Yet God doth oft times work mediately or by the uſe of means. And this he doth, not for want of power, for he is <hi>El-ſhaddai, the Almighty God</hi> Gen. 17. 1. But that (through the abundance of his goodneſs and bounty) he may communicate a certain dignity of working with him to his creatures alſo, and may thereby make his efficacy more perſpicuous. <hi>We are</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle 1 Cor. 3. 9.) <hi>labourers together with God,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Men and other creatures work with God, but under God, and by his direction for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his deſigns, even as God wrought by Jonathan and his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor-bearer to the diſcomfiture, and total rout of the Philiſtines, 1 Sam. 14. 6-16.</p>
            <p>Thus God worketh the ſafety or ruine of Kingdoms and great Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by Counſels, Armyes, and ſuch like means.</p>
            <p>Of this mediate working of God, this Text and Doctrine is to be underſtood. Counſellors and their counſels are Inſtruments and Tools in Gods hand, which he ſometimes uſeth, and ſometimes he breaketh, as ſeemeth good unto him. He ſometimes maketh the moſt fit means (as to the judgment and apprehenſion of man), to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119995:7"/> prove in effectual to accompliſh the end intended; And ſometimes he produceth the moſt noble effects by thoſe ways and means which of themſelves have no aptitude to bring forth thoſe effects.</p>
            <p>And God worketh thus, to the end that our Faith may not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly reſpect thoſe means which God uſeth, nor depend onely or, chiefly upon them; but upon God alone, who can relieve all our wants and neceſſityes, with means, or without means, as it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth good unto him. And indeed this is the excellency of Faith, when a Chriſtian taketh up that noble reſolution of <hi>Shadrach, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> Dan. 3. 17. <hi>Our God whom we ſerve is able to deliver us from the fiery Fornace, and he will deliver us from thine hand O King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What therefore I ſhall ſay of the proſperity, or adverſity of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and People, or of Kingdoms and Commonwealths, in regard of their dependance upon Counſellors and Counſels, muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood as they are ſubordinate unto, and co-operating with the mind, decree, and providence of God. For <hi>there is no wiſdom, nor underſtanding; nor counſel againſt the Lord; The horſe is prepared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the day of battel; but ſafety is of the Lord,</hi> as our wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerveth, Prov. 21. 30, 31.</p>
            <p>Much time needeth not be ſpent in the proof of this point, which of it ſelf is ſo perſpicuous. Obſerve it onely in three particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1 This Maſter of Politicks <hi>(Solomon)</hi> doth oft times repeat this as an undoubted truth. He telleth us Prov. 15. 22. <hi>That without Counſel purpoſes are diſappointed, but in the multitude of Counſellors they are eſtabliſhed;</hi> And Chap. 20. 18. <hi>Every purpoſe is eſtabliſhed by Counſel;</hi> And again Chap. 24. 6. <hi>In multitude of Counſellors there is ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Unto this mediate cauſe it is that alſo the Lord himſelf doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the proſperity, or ruine of Kings and their Kingdoms. The Lord informeth us, That <hi>Rehoboams</hi> miſery, came upon him by neglecting the counſel of the Sages that had ſtood before his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, their Advice had been his welfare if he had hearkened unto it. 2. Chron. 10. 8-14. And the word of God mindeth us that it was the deſtruction of <hi>Ahaziah</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> that he hearkened unto the wicked counſel of his Mother, and others that were of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119995:8"/> houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> 2. Chron. 22. 3-5. On the otherſide, It was the wiſdom of <hi>David,</hi> and that which did ſtrengthen him in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, That in all weighty caſes <hi>he conſulted with the Captains of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and hundreds, and with every leader, even with all the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of</hi> Iſrael, 1. Chron. 13. 1-4. He would not act without Counſel.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Even the Law of nature by its glimmering, doth dictate this truth to all civillized Nations, That they ſhould have their great Counſels and Counſellors, with whom to adviſe in all matters of moment; The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had their <hi>Sanhedri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> The <hi>Lacedaemonians</hi> had their <hi>Ephori,</hi> The <hi>Athenians</hi> had their <hi>Demarchi,</hi> The <hi>Romans</hi> had their <hi>Senate,</hi> The <hi>Germans</hi> have their <hi>Diets.</hi> We in theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have our <hi>Parliaments;</hi> Yea the <hi>Indians</hi> have ſome kind of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils; All Nations know that without counſels they cannot well ſubſiſt, that by counſels their ſafety is maintained.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why the proſperity, or adverſity of a People depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth very much upon their Counſellors and Counſels, is, becauſe <hi>Counſel is the guide of all actions.</hi> The tranſacting of great Affairs without Counſel, is like the riding upon a wild colt without bit or bridle, it is a thouſand to one that the rider is caſt. Raſh proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings without deliberate Advice, do make Affairs miſcarry. Gods own Counſel and decree took place before his works, he ſaid <hi>Let it be ſo,</hi> and ſo, before he wrought any work in the Creation, Gen. 1. 3. 6. 9. Counſel is like the helm of a Ship, if that be wanting, the veſſel is in danger to be daſhed in pieces againſt the rocks; if that be ſound it ſteereth the ſhip through all winds and tempeſts untill it arrive at its deſired haven.</p>
            <p>The Uſes of this Doctrine are three. 1 Of information 2 Of praiſe and thankſgiving. 3 Of exhortation. Of theſe I ſhall ſpeak in order.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Uſe of this point is for information, and that again di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videth it ſelf into two branches.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If it be ſo, That the proſperity or ruine of a people dependeth ſo much upon Counſellors and counſels, then this informeth us of the <hi>abominable wickedneſs,</hi> and <hi>deſperate madneſs</hi> of thoſe men in theſe Dominions, who have endeavored to bereave us of our Counſellors and counſels, they have done what they can to deſtroy us.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119995:8"/>
            <p> That there have been and are ſuch, yea many ſuch in this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, I need not ſpend time to demonſtrate. Our too dear bought experience for diverſe years by paſt doth ſufficiently inform us; ſo that the very Perſons that have been the chief actors may be pointed out by the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> names.</p>
            <p>The Anabaptiſts, the Quakers, and even all thoſe that have ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the Church of Chriſt in theſe Nations, have ſo interru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted our counſels, diſmembred our Parliament, and ſupplanted our laws and birth privileges; that it may be ſaid of us, as once it was ſaid of Iſrael 2 Chron. 15. 3. <hi>Now for a long ſeaſon England, Ireland and Scotland have been without Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who hath not felt the direfull effects of theſe mens fury, upon their perſons, families and eſtates, yea and upon our Religion alſo? So that we are all brought thereby to the very brink of ruine and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Of theſe men I affirm two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That it is <hi>abominable wickedneſs</hi> in them that have acted thus, to the diſmembring and interruption of our Parliament, or great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil; they have contributed what they could to the overthrow of theſe Dominions.</p>
            <p>It is a great ſin to contrive the death, or ruine of a ſingle perſon onely. David complaineth of this as a great fault in his adverſaries, Pſal. 31. 13. <hi>They deviſed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to take away my life.</hi> How much greater is their ſin that have endeavored to cut off the Head of three great Nations at one blow?</p>
            <p>And this their ſin is the greater upon a twofold account.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Becauſe they have deviſed this miſchief againſt thoſe that truſted them, and looked upon them as their friend,, received them into their counſels, put Commiſſions, Arms, Ammunition, Treaſure into their hands, and expected the ſupport of Religion, Laws, Liberties, Parliaments by their means.</p>
            <p>So that we may well complain with the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 55. 12-14. <hi>It was not an Enemy that reproached me, then could I have born it; neither was it he that hated me that magnifyed himſelf againſt me, then I would have hid my ſelf from him. But it was thou, mine equal, my guide, and mine acquaintance. We took ſweet Counſel to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and walked unto the Houſe of God in company.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119995:9"/>
            <p> O this is a great aggravation of their offence, that <hi>they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed evil against their neighbours that dwell ſecurely by them,</hi> Prov. 3. 29. Treachery againſt truſt is ſuperlative wickedneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Becauſe, they have done all this wrong to the Commonwealth under a pretence of Religion; as if thereby they ſhould advance the Kingdom and Intereſt of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe perſons have dreamed certain dreams of the perſonal reign of Chriſt upon earth, and of their own Saint-ſhip; and holyneſs, as the onely perſons fit to reign with him; and from hence they have endeavoured to ſet up for themſelves, and to take the whole Earth into their poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>piae fraudes</hi> are thoſe cheats which are moſt abominable both before God and man.</p>
            <p>But can they think to have any thanks from the Lord Jeſus for ſeeking to advance his Intereſt, by ſubverting his ſtanding Laws of Magiſtracy and Miniſtry? Or is this the way to introduce the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt, to trample thoſe great Ordinances and Inſtitutions under foot? I trow not. By his written word they muſt be judged, at his glorious appearing and in his Kingdom; which word ſaith thus. Rom. 13. 1. <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher powers.</hi> And 1. Pet. 2 13-15. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake.—For ſo is the will of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe perſons learned not this leſſon of the good old Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, who were diſgracefully called by the name of Puritans; but of <hi>Stock,</hi> and <hi>Muncer,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leiden,</hi> and other Rebels, Apoſtates from the reformed Religion. And therefore it is pity that their miſcarriages ſhould be caſt in the teeth of any honeſt and ſober Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>But it is no new thing to commit Treaſons under the vizzard of holineſs. The Apoſtle long ſince foretold that there ſhould be <hi>trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, heady, high minded</hi> perſons <hi>having a form of godlineſs.</hi> 2. Tim. 3. 1-5. This Propheſy is eminently fulfilled in theſe our backſliding times. By their means our holy and good profeſſion is ſcandalized, and <hi>the way of truth is evil spoken of</hi> by Papiſts and Atheiſts, and all profane men, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh 2 Pet. 2. 2.</p>
            <p n="2">II. It is alſo <hi>deſperate madneſs</hi> in them to act after this rate, for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119995:9"/> the extirpation of our counſellors and their counſells. For; If they had accompliſhed their deſigns, could they have eſcaped ſcot-free in the common overthrow?</p>
            <p>Who but a man bereft of his wits, will ſink the veſſel wherein he is imbarked? or fire the houſe wherein he dwelleth?</p>
            <p>Wherefore they are to be looked upon, and dealt withal as mad man uſe to be, being fitter for bedlam then for ſober ſociety. The poſſeſſed of the Devil uſed to be <hi>bound in chains and fetters,</hi> Mar. 5. 4. You cannot deal too warily with this generation of men.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If it be ſo, That the proſperity or adverſity of a people dependeth ſo much upon counſellors and counſels, Then this alſo informeth us, of the great worth and excellency of thoſe honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perſons, who have ventured their all for the reſtitution of our Grand Council the Parliament, they have done what in them is to keep theſe Nations from utter ruine and confuſion. This is true No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</p>
            <p>This was it that made <hi>Saul</hi> honourable in the eyes of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> when he ſtood up ſo manfully for the preſervation, and deliverance of the inhabitants of <hi>Jabeſh-Gilead,</hi> 1. Sam. 11.</p>
            <p>Certainly ſuch Worthies deſerve well from us, and from our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; We ſhould all ſay with <hi>Deborah</hi> in her ſong, Judg. 5. 9. <hi>My heart is toward the Governors of</hi> Iſrael <hi>that offered themſelves willingly among the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know full well what ſome black mouths belch out againſt theſe Noble perſons, and Saviours of our countrey, and againſt the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates of this famous City. But let them alone, when they are come to themſelves they will be wiſer, and conſider, That it was a duty to ſave three Nations from ſinking into deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And as thankfulneſs, love and honor are due from us all unto them; So they may expect a reward from God for this incomparable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice done to the Church and Nations, Yea, and God will reward them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If a cup of cold water given to</hi> any <hi>one in the name of a diſciple, ſhall not be unrewarded,</hi> Mat. 10. 42. What then ſhall the reward of thoſe be, that have ventured Life, Eſtate, and all that is dear unto them, to ſave this Republique, wherein are a multitude of true diſciples of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:119995:10"/>
            <p> The ſecond Uſe of this Doctrine affordeth ground of praiſe and thanksgiving unto the Lord our God for two great mercies.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If the want of counſellors doth portend the fall of a people; Then, what abundant cauſe have we all to bleſs the Lord, that theſe Dominions are not totally ruined ere this day, by the ſecluding of our counſellors, and interrupting their counſels for ſo many years together?</p>
            <p>You ſee that ſuch a want of councel as we have had, is uſually the fall of a people, and yet herein God hath been more mercifull to us than to others; although we were plunged into the ditch, yet we are not quite drowned. We may ſay truly with the Pſalmiſt, Pſal. 118, 13. <hi>Thou haſt thrust ſore at me that I might fall, but the Lord helped me.</hi> And verſe 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>This is the Lords doing, and it is marvelous in our eyes.</hi> You muſt ſet a <hi>Selah</hi> upon this mercie, and ſay, <hi>Hitherto hath the Lord helped us.</hi> The 124 Pſalm and the 129 Pſalm ought to be ſung frequently by all the godly in theſe Nations in comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of this mercie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If it be ſo, That the flouriſhing eſtate of a people ariſeth from their enjoyment of a multitude of Counſellors, Then what cauſe have we to praiſe the name of the Lord, that he hath at laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored unto us our Free Parliament, that great Council, that may ſave us from deſtruction and ruine?</p>
            <p>God hath this day begun to perform unto us that gracious promiſe which he made to the Jews Iſa. 1. 26. <hi>I will reſtore thy Judges as at the firſt, and thy Counſellors as at the beginning.</hi> It is a wonder of mercie, that the Lord hath done this great thing for us.</p>
            <p>And it is a great addition of mercy to us in this Iſland, that God hath raiſed up to us alſo ſo many worthy Counſellors in this poor peeled Nation, and hath (notwithſtanding manifold obſtructions which were in the way) brought them together into this City, to conſult and adviſe of thoſe things that ſo nearly concern us, both in matters religious and civil.</p>
            <p>That both theſe mercies I am ſpeaking of may have the greater im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon our hearts, conſider ſeriouſly theſe four things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Our own unworthineſs for whom God hath appeared ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently. Well may we take up that humble expreſſion of Jacob Gen:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119995:10"/> 32. 10. <hi>We are not worthy of the leaſt of all the mercies, and of all the truth which thou haſt ſhewed unto thy ſervants;</hi> much leſs of ſo great mercy and truth as hath appeared in theſe mercies that we are now ſpeaking of.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Look upon the depth of the miſery that we were plunged into, and that will illuſtrate the greatneſs of theſe mercies; our laws were diſcountenanced, our properties impropriated, our liberties infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; yea and which is more, our ſelves were unchurched, ſome of our godly Miniſters ſilenced and baniſhed, and the Goſpel ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from us, and nothing but blackneſs and darkneſs of error coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced and encouraged, to the wounding of the hearts of all truly pious men.</p>
            <p>The actings of theſe late times have been like the Rebellion of Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, Dathan and Abiram, that ſtrove againſt Moſes and Aaron; of which you may read Numb. Ch. 16. They endeavoured to pull down Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, and ſo have theſe done.</p>
            <p>Dathan and Abiram were Gentlemen of the tribe of <hi>Reuben the eldest ſon of Iſrael</hi> Num. 26. 5. <hi>Famous in the Congregation</hi> Verſe 9. They thought they had as much right to the civil Government as Moſes had; and therefore ſay they (ſpeaking in the Levellers dialect) <hi>Why lift you up your ſelves above the congregation of the Lord?</hi> in the third verſe. And when they were ſummoned by Moſes, they refuſed appear, Ch. 16. v. 12. 13. <hi>We will not come up,</hi> (ſay they) <hi>Is it a ſmall thing, that thou haſt brought us up out of a land that floweth with milk and hony, to kill us in the wilderneſs, except thou make thy ſelf altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Prince over us?</hi> Their quarrel againſt Moſes was about civil power, they would needs aſſume the ſupreme Magiſtracy.</p>
            <p>Korah was a Levite, and he would have none above him in the Church, he would needs do the Office of a Prieſt aſwell as Aaron, as appeareth verſe 10, 11. His quarrel was eccleſiaſtical he would level the Prieſts Office and make it common, becauſe all the people had the gifts of the ſpirit; <hi>The congregation</hi> (ſaith he verſe 3.) <hi>are holy every one of them, and the Lord is among them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame thing that they did hath been acting over again upon the theatre of theſe lands. The Apoſtle Jude verſe 11 tells you that the ſin of Korah may be committed in the days of the Goſpel.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119995:11"/>
            <p> If this have not been the time of killing the two Witneſſes ſpoken of Revel. 11. 7. I am ſure it is very like to it, a very few years will inform us more fully.</p>
            <p>Now Gods appearance for us in ſuch a time doth make the mercy ſo much the greater.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Conſider the way whereby the Lord began to work up our hopes for deliverance and reſtitution to our priſtine condition. He ſets the adverſaries themſelves at odds, they that had ingroſſed all the power, riches and great Offices into their hands, quarrel who ſhould be the greateſt. The military Anabaptiſts reach further than their ſleeve would ſtretch, in regard of power and command, they reſolve to win all or to loſe all. But <hi>in the thing wherein they dealt proudly, God was above them</hi> Exod. 18. 11. Their diviſions were the ſignal omen of our deliverance and their own ruine.</p>
            <p>So that we may well take up that of David Pſal. 7. 14-16. <hi>Behold he travelleth with iniquity, and hath conceived miſchief, and brought forth falſehood, he made a pit and digged it, and is fallen into the ditch which he made, His miſchief ſhall return upon his own head, and his vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent dealing ſhall come down upon his own pate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Laſtly, Obſerve what eminent inſtruments God hath raiſed up to carry on this great work, after the enemies themſelves had begun it; even by perſons unthought of hath God wrought both in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Ireland and Scotland; raiſing up the hearts even of multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of the common people to ſtand for the Parliament.</p>
            <p>All theſe things conferred together do make Gods mercies in theſe deliverances to ſhine moſt gloriouſly.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt Uſe of this Doctrine is for Exhortation, which alſo will divide it ſelf into two parts. For (in handling this Uſe) I would direct my ſpeech 1 To all here preſent in general, 2 To you (our honorable and grave Counſellors) in particular.</p>
            <p>Exhort. 1. And firſt this Doctrine ſpeaketh generally to all here preſent, and to all others in this land, who have had an hand or voice in the election of theſe honorable Perſons to be your Repreſentatives in this great Convention, or that do expect to receive any benefit by them as inſtruments in Gods hand for your good.</p>
            <p>You muſt carry it ſo toward them, as you would do toward ſuch
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119995:11"/> from whom you expect ſafety, and to be kept from falling.</p>
            <p>This duty of yours toward them whom God hath ſet up to be the conſervators of your peace, I ſhall lay down and illuſtrate in Four particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1 You muſt honor, love and reſpect them, as thoſe that are to be your Saviours, prize them as Gods ordinance, for the procuring of your ſafety, and deliverance from deſtruction.</p>
            <p>When the Apoſtle had ſpoken of Magiſtracy, and the protection we recieve from it, Rom. 13. 1-4. he maketh this Uſe of that he had taught, in the 7. Verſe, <hi>Render therefore to all their dues, Honour to whom honour is due.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, the Magiſtrate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth honour for the ſafety you recieve by his means.</p>
            <p>The Heathens uſed to Deify their <hi>Heroes</hi> for thoſe noble acts they had done for them; herein they exceeded their due bounds and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits; But we that are called Chriſtians uſually fall too ſhort in our eſteem of Magiſtrates, we give them not the honour due to them.</p>
            <p>This is foul ingratitude, to deny honour to thoſe that are the means under God of our ſafety</p>
            <p n="2">2 You muſt not paſs raſh cenſures upon what they ſhall act in your name, and for your good. It is a great fault in many, (both Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and others,) that they pry too far into the Ark of State, and when their eyes dazzle, then they ſpeak evil of the things they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not, it were better for ſuch to keep themſelves within the compaſs of their own callings. It is too diſingenuous to cenſure thoſe Perſons that have been choſen by us, and do act (according to their abilities) for our good. <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods</hi> (ſaith the Lord, Exod. 22. 28.) <hi>nor curſe the ruler of thy people.</hi> Whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, backbiters, murmurers, complainers upon every ſuppoſed oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, are the refuſe of the people. A <hi>Moſes</hi> cannot ſcape the laſh of ſuch mens tongues.</p>
            <p n="3">3 You muſt yeild ſubjection to ſuch things as they ſhall agree upon for your good, to ſuch Ordinances as they ſhall make on your behalf.</p>
            <p>They are the perſons who are intruſted in this Land, for ordering your publique affairs, Wherefore <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er powers,</hi> Rom. 13. 1.</p>
            <p>You muſt ſubmit to them, even in thoſe neceſſary Taxes and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119995:12"/> that muſt by their advice be leavyed for your defence. <hi>For this cauſe</hi> (that is, becauſe of the protection you receive from Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy, Rom. 13. 6.) <hi>Pay you tribute alſo.</hi> Souldiers muſt be paid their wages, and the charge of other publique buſineſſes muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayed, or elſe you will fall into unavoidable miſery.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Laſtly, and eſpecially. You muſt pray for them. The Nation is heart ſick, theſe are your Phyſicians, you can do no leſs then pray for a bleſſing from God upon thoſe means they ſhall make uſe of for your cure and healing.</p>
            <p>Mark well the advice the Apoſtle giveth, 1. Tim. 2. 1. 2. <hi>I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort therefore that firſt of all Supplications, Prayers, Interceſſions, and giving of thanks be made for all men; For Kings and for all that are in authority, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and honeſty.</hi> You muſt pray for them with all kind of prayer, and if you do your duty in this particular, the Apoſtle aſſureth you of three benefits you ſhall obtain by it. 1 The Church ſhall enjoy more <hi>peace</hi> by this means. 2 <hi>Honeſty,</hi> that is, juſtice, and fidelity in the civil converſation of men, will be the better preſerved. 3. <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> true piety and Religion will proſper by this means.</p>
            <p>And the rather muſt you pay this debt at this time upon a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold account, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Becauſe, Our counſels have not been ſucceſsful for many years by paſt, they have not accompliſhed the things we hoped for either in Church or State, but things have grown worſe and worſe.</p>
            <p>And we have cauſe to impute this great obſtruction to this, That we have not prayed for a bleſſing upon our counſellors and their counſells, or at leaſt, That we have not prayed in that manner as we ought. <hi>Ye fight and war</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle Jam. 4. 2. and ſo may we ſay) <hi>yet ye have not.</hi> Why? <hi>Becauſe ye ask not,</hi> That is our fault. And though <hi>ye ask yet ye recieve not</hi> (ſaith he Verſe 3. Why?) <hi>becauſe ye ask amiſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It never ſped well with our counſels ſince our publique Faſts were neglected<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and turned into private meetings; upon what account I know not, unleſs it was done to gratify and promote the way of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration.</p>
            <p>It will never ſpeed well with our Counſells, nor with the Church
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119995:12"/> of God in this Land, till our publique Faſts be reſtored, and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them that ſuſtain the higheſt place of power among us; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the famous examples of the moſt pious and renowned Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> as <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> 2. Chron. 20. 3. and others.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as it hath been the laudable practiſe of all godly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, to proclaim Faſts to be publiquely obſerved throughout their Territories, when any grievous calamity hath been felt or fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or when they have wanted ſpecial mercies, or have enterpriſed ſome difficult matter: I therefore humbly offer; whether it be not convenient, and neceſſary upon all theſe accounts, That a publique Faſt be appointed to be obſerved throughout this whole Land.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Becauſe, The affairs which are under hand, are of great import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; our ſafety, or our ruine depending much thereupon; as you may ſee by that Religious and full Declaration ſet forth the ſixteenth day of <hi>February</hi> laſt paſt. You expect that God ſhould do much for you by this honourable Convention, that your Religion, Lives Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertyes, Eſtates ſhall be ſecured by their means; But you muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, That God <hi>will be enquired of by you that he may do</hi> all theſe things by them, as it is in Ezek. 36. 27.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Becauſe, If ye pray, ye have promiſes that ye ſhall receive great benefit thereby. I ſhall onely mind you of one promiſe made in this caſe, Iſa, 58. 9. 12. <hi>Thou ſhalt call and the Lord ſhall anſwer.—And they that ſhall be of thee ſhall build the old waſte places, thou ſhalt raiſe up the foundations of many generations, and thou ſhalt be called the repairer of the breach, the restorer of paths to dwell in.</hi> O that this gracious promiſe may be made good to this Church and Nation at this time, but prayer is the condition on our part.</p>
            <p>Exhort. 2. And now I muſt addreſs my ſelf to you (our honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and grave Senators) upon whom all our eyes are fixed, in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of help and ſafety under the ſhadow of your wings, from thoſe great miſeries that threaten us at this time.</p>
            <p>And I beſeech you to <hi>bear with me,</hi> and to allow me <hi>freedom of ſpeech,</hi> that I may deliver the Lords meſſage to you, <hi>ſpeaking as I ought to ſpeak.</hi> And yet I ſhall (through the divine aſſiſtance) keep my ſelf within the limits of my calling, leaſt by any means the Office of <hi>the Miniſtry ſhould be blamed</hi> through my default.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119995:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> That which I have unto you from the Lord ſhall be couched under two heads. 1 Be ye ſuch Counſellors as may ſave the people from falling. 2 Let your Counſells be ſuch as may procure their ſafety. The firſt appertains to the Qualifications of your Perſons, The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond relateth to your Actings. Of them I ſhall ſpeak diſtinctly.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I intreat, and earneſtly exhort you in the Lord, that ye ſtudy to be ſuch perſons as may prevent our deſtruction.</p>
            <p>It is not every one that is meet to be in ſuch a place of honour and truſt, as to be accounted a Saviour of the Land; thoſe onely are to be in this employment, that are fitted of the Lord. and ſpirited with due Qualifications to this great work. Now I ſhall lay this down in Five particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1 You that are to be members of this great Council, had need to be men truely fearing the Lord, Pious, Holy, and Gracious Perſons.</p>
            <p>They that are called to places of judgment in a Nation, are ſtiled <hi>Gods,</hi> Pſal. 82. 1. 6. They are Gods Lievtenants, do repreſent his Majeſty and Soveraignty. Holineſs is that image of God that you ought eſpecially to bear, to make you fit for this high undertaking, that ought in an eminent manner to be engraven upon your hearts and foreheads. This was that qualification which God himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth to be in thoſe that were to be Judges in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Deut. 18. 21. <hi>Thou ſhalt provide out of all the people able men, ſuch as fear God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if the fear of God be in you, if ye ſtrive after holineſs of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and converſation, then ye cannot much miſcarry in your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of</hi> all ſound <hi>wiſdom,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, Job 28. 28. Sound counſel floweth thence.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Ye have a promiſe of direction in your counſells if ye be truly religious and holy, Pſalm 25. 9. <hi>The meek will he guide in judgment;</hi> and Verſe 14. <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him.</hi> They ſhall be of his cabinet counſel, and receive advice from him.</p>
            <p>Pious Counſellors, (though they be not ſo knowing or prudent as others are,) will be the beſt ſafety of a people. Of ſuch it is that <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſpeaketh. Job 22. 28. <hi>Thou ſhalt decree a thing and it ſhall be eſtabliſhed unto thee, and the light ſhall ſhine upon thy ways.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II Ye had need to be wiſe, prudent and experienced men that are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119995:13"/> to be Pilots of our leaking veſſel, which is toſſed with ſo many tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts and contrary winds and tides, elſe we are not likely to get into a ſafe harbour.</p>
            <p>If wiſdom be wanting in counſellors it portendeth ruine approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This was it that proclaimed the deſtruction of <hi>Egypt</hi> to be near at hand, Iſa. 19. 11. <hi>Surely the Princes of</hi> Zoan <hi>are fools, the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the wiſe counſellors is become brutiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other ſide, if the counſellors of a nation be wiſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding men, then proſperity is likely to befal ſuch a people.</p>
            <p>This was the juſt commendation of Ahitophel (though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a moſt wicked and ungodly man) <hi>That the counſel which he did counſel, was as if a man had enquired at the Oracle of God, ſo</hi> (ſaith the Holy Ghoſt 2 Sam. 16. 23.) <hi>was all the counſel of Ahitophel, both with David and with Abſalom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Counſellors had need to underſtand the Laws of the Land, to be well ſeen in the cuſtoms and uſages of the people, to know the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Countries, the practiſes of former ages, and the ſtate of the preſent times.</p>
            <p>It is recorded of the chief Heads of the children of Iſſachar that came to Hebron to make David King. 1 Chron. 12. 32. That <hi>they were men that had underſtanding of the times, to know what Iſrael ought to do.</hi> Some underſtand it, that they had knowledg in Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, by which they did foreſee the natural diſpoſitions of ſeaſons, and diverſe accidents of inferior bodies, depending on the influence and government of the celeſtial ones; which Science is not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unlawful in it ſelf, though the practiſers of judicial Aſtrology ſeldom keep within their lawful bounds. But I rather underſtand it thus, That they were men endued with ſingular wiſdom and ſaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, either natural, or acquired by long experience; whereby they were able to diſcern and know the very moment of opportunities; which is a thing very important, and whereupon ordinarily depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the good ſucceſs of affairs. Of this the wiſe man admoniſheth, Eccl. 3. 1. That <hi>to every thing there is a ſeaſon, und a time to every purpoſe under the ſun.</hi> And verſe 11. <hi>Every thing is beautiful in its time.</hi> To time a buſineſs aright is the excellencie of wiſdom.</p>
            <p>Upon the wiſdom or the miſtakes in counſels, there doth uſually
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119995:14"/> follow anſwerable events. Wherefore when the Lord intendeth to deſtroy a People, he doth uſually in the firſt place infatuate their counſels, according to that of the Prophet, Iſa. 44. 25. <hi>He fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the tokens of the lyers, and maketh diviners mad, he turneth wiſe men backward, and maketh their knowledg fooliſh:</hi> And <hi>hath not God made fooliſh the wiſdom of this world?</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle 1 Cor. 1. 20.</p>
            <p>You ſee then what an extraordinary meaſure of knowledg you had need to have to capacitate you for this great buiſineſs. Daniel was judged meet to be called unto the Kings Council, becauſe the ſpirit of <hi>the holy</hi> God <hi>was in him, even an excellent ſpirit in knowledg and underſtanding and wiſdom</hi> Dan. 5. 11, 12.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Ye ought to be men of publique ſpirits, and muſt be ſuch, if ever ye intend to be a protection and ſafety to the people. Private, ſelf-ſeeking men are not fit to be employed in publique counſels<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>When God called Solomon to bear the Kingly Office in Iſrael, it is ſaid 1 King 4. 29. That he <hi>gave him largeneſs of heart, even as the ſand that is on the ſea ſhore,</hi> he was not of a ſtraitned, ſelf intereſted temper. I crave leave to enlarge my ſelf in a few particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Ye muſt reſolve to ſerve your Country though ye cannot profit your ſelves at all thereby, but ſhould rather waſte your own outward eſtates. Nehemiah for <hi>twelve years</hi> together <hi>did not eat the bread of the Governor</hi> (when the people were in diſtreſs) <hi>as the former Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors had done.</hi> Neh. 5. 14, 15. An excellent pattern. Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, purſuing after a private profit in publique matters may well be called <hi>pestis Reipublicae;</hi> this is a ſpecial thing to be avoided by them that are to judg others Deut. 18. 21. they muſt <hi>hate covetouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 A publique ſpirit will not ſuffer injuries of any ſort to be put upon the people; he beareth with and putteth up private in juries with patience, but that wrong that is offered to the publique goeth to his heart, he cannot brook it. It was a noble virtue, and a publique ſpirit in Saul, that when a private deſpite was done unto himſelf, yet he did <hi>hold his peace</hi> and was ſilent 1 Sam. 10. 27. But when he heard of the wrong done to his Subjects the men of Jabeſh-Gilead by Nahaſh the Ammonite, the Text ſaith, that <hi>the ſpirit of God came upon</hi> Saul when he heard theſe tidings, and <hi>his anger was kindled greatly,</hi> 1 Sam. 11. 6. and he reſted not till he had relieved them.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119995:14"/> 3 A publique ſpirit is more ſenſible of the peoples ſufferings and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, then of any private mercies that concern himſelf onely. See this in good Nehemiah, although he was in high honour, cup-bearer to a great King, yet he minded not that, but his countenance was ſad and his heart full of ſorrow, when he heard of the great affliction and reproach that was befallen his country-men, <hi>Why ſhould not my countenance be ſad</hi> (ſaith he Neh. 2. 2, 3.) <hi>when the city, the place of my fathers ſepulchres lyeth waste, and the gates thereof are conſumed with fire.</hi> So alſo Uriah denieth his own private content upon a publique account, 2 Sam. 11. 11. <hi>The Ark, and Iſrael, and Judah a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in Tents, and my Lord Joab, and the ſervants of my Lord are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped in the open fields, ſhall I then go into my houſe to eat, and to drink and to ly with my wife? as the Lord liveth, and as thy ſoul liveth, I will not do this thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 A publique ſpirit will not ſtick at his own private danger though it be apparant, but will venture his own perſon to the greateſt haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, ſo that he may further the publique intereſt. He will uſe his ſword aſwell as his tongue if neceſſity require it. David did <hi>fight the Lords battels</hi> 1 Sam. 10, 17. When religion is in danger, he will not ſpare himſelf, but venture life and limb to uphold it. Excellent was the reſolution of Queen Eſther in this caſe, Chap. 4. 16. <hi>I will go in unto the King, which is not according to the Law, and if I periſh, I periſh.</hi> He knoweth that he is not born for himſelf, but for his country alſo, and can willingly dye in the ſervice thereof. He can ſay as that reverend Biſhop did, <hi>Moriar ego modo me moriente vigeat Eccleſiae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 He that hath a publique ſpirit deſireth rather to be uſeful in his generation then to be great. When the Lord puts <hi>Solomon</hi> to his choiſe what he would have, 1 King. 3. 5. He beggeth nothing but a publique ſpirit Verſe 9. <hi>Give thy ſervant an underſtanding heart to judge thy people, that I may diſcern between good and bad; for who is able to judge this thy ſo great a people.</hi> He asketh not honour and grandure in the world, but that he might be uſeful to the people of God over whom he was placed.</p>
            <p n="6">6 I will adde but one thing more, A man that hath the publique upon his heart, will lay aſide all private animoſities, put up all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119995:15"/> wrongs and differences, rather then endanger the publique peace and ſettlement of the people. When there was ſome private difference between <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> occaſioned by their herd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whence the <hi>Canaanite</hi> and <hi>Perizzite</hi> (who dwelt in the land) might have taken an opportunity to have done hurt to both of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we find that <hi>Abraham</hi> paſſeth over that difference, and would take no notice of it to the publique diſadvantage. Gen. 13. 7. 8. 9. <hi>Let there be no ſtrife. I pray thee, between me and thee, and between my herdmen and thy herdmen; for we be brethren. Is not the whole land before thee, ſeperate I pray thee thy ſelf from me, if thou wilt take the left hand then I will go to she right, or if thou depart to the right hand then I will go to the left.</hi> If the mariners fall out the ſhip muſt needs be in jeopardy. If private grudges be in the heart, the publique con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments are like to ſuffer.</p>
            <p>I have the rather preſſed this duty of publique ſpiritedneſs upon you (worthy Patriots,) becauſe you know as well as I, that private intereſt, and ſelf ſeeking in publique affairs, have for a long time by paſt deſtroyed all our national counſells and conſultations.</p>
            <p n="4">IIII Ye ought to be of ſettled and well reſolved ſpirits, and full of courage for God and your country. To this end ye have your ſwords girt.</p>
            <p>How ſhall ye be able to perſevere in ſeeking the good of Gods houſe, or of the Nation, if ye be not reſolved and grounded in your Religion, and in the Laws of the Land? And eſpecially is it requiſite at this time that ye be full of immoveable reſolution, becauſe there is ſuch a multitude of unſtable ſpirits in the land, who change in their principles upon every occaſion, of whom ye are admoniſhed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware. Prov. 24. 21. <hi>My ſon fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change.</hi> Hearken not unto them, have nothing to do with them that are every day deviſing a new cut in regard of religious and civil matters. And he giveth you fix Reaſons againſt this unſetledneſs of ſpirit, and againſt intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with them that are ſo changeable in Verſe 22. <hi>For their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the ruine of them both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Calamity ſhall be the portion both of theſe changlings, and of thoſe that meddle with them, <hi>their calamity</hi> ſhall riſe <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neither
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119995:15"/> of them ſhall eſcape danger. <hi>Gideous</hi> idolatry in making an Ephod, &amp; putting it in his own city, <hi>became a ſnare</hi> to him and to his houſe, and to all <hi>Iſrael</hi> Judg. 8. 27. it brought much miſery upon them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This calamity <hi>ſhall riſe,</hi> as a bird out of the buſh unthought of, by ſuch ways and means as are not by us imaginable, by ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary hand of God. As it fell out with King <hi>Uzziah,</hi> who would needs invade the Prieſts office to burn incenſe in the temple, but the Lord in a miraculous manner plagued him, <hi>the leproſy even roſe upin his forehead</hi> ſaith the Text 2. Chron. 26. 19.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It ſhall riſe <hi>ſuddenly,</hi> before it can be thought of, Prov. 6. 15. <hi>Tberefore his calamity come ſuddenly, ſuddenly ſhall he be broken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remedy.</hi> They ſhall have no time to parley with it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This calamity ſhall end in <hi>ruine,</hi> in a total deſtruction; the miſery of ſuch perſons ſhall be capital, <hi>Thou woundedſt the head out of the houſe of the wicked,</hi> ſaith Habbakkuk in his prayer Chap. 3. 13. God will utterly deſtroy them.</p>
            <p n="5">5 It ſhall be the ruine <hi>of them both,</hi> They that are given to change, and they that meddle with them, ſhall fare both alike. Not onely Korah, Dathan and Abiram did periſh for their innovation in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters appertaining to religion and civil government, but alſo thoſe two hundred and fifty princes that were enſnared by them, and drawn into that mutany, as you find Numb 16. 31-35.</p>
            <p n="6">6 This ruine ſhall be unexpreſſible, unconceivable, <hi>Who knoweth</hi> it? who is able to declare how great it ſhall be?</p>
            <p>Ye ſhall not doubt have many giddy phanatick ſpirits fawning up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, who will ſeek to unſettle your judgments, and to turn you out of the right and old way; for theſe croaking frogs ſwarm in every corner. Therefore ſtand your ground, be well reſolved in your own judgments.</p>
            <p>And as you muſt be well ſettled in your judgments, ſo you muſt take good courage to carry on the work before you, and to withſtand all difficulties you ſhall encounter with. This befitteth your place. <hi>Be ſtrong and of a good courage,</hi> ſaith the Lord to Joſhua Ch. 1. 6, 7, 9. And ſtir up one another in the words of Joab 2 Sam. 10. 12. <hi>Be of good courage, and let us play the men, for our people, and for the Cities of our God; and the Lord do that which ſeemeth him good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:119995:16"/> V. Laſtly, Ye muſt alſo be unanimous, of one heart, and of one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in your counſels and conſultations, elſe ye ſhall never be able to ſave the people from falling. Though Counſellors be many and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, yet if they fall to diviſion among themſelves and ſide into par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and make factions, the people can have no hope of ſafety and protection from them, but muſt needs be in continual fears and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies.</p>
            <p>This was it that put the Iſraelites into very ſad thoughts in the time of their war againſt Jabin the King of Canaan, becauſe that the Reubenites were divided from them in that enterprize, and made more account of their own ſecurity, than of employing themſelves any way for the aſſiſtance of their brethren in that common danger; Judg. 5. 15, 16. <hi>For the diviſions of Reuben there were great ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diviſions and factions in counſels are ſad ſigns to a Land, or to a particular perſon. When that Ahitophel counſelled Abſalom to fall upon David while he was weary and weak-handed; and on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſide, Huſhai adviſed to protract the time untill a great army could be prepared to fight a ſet battel 2 Sam. 17. 1-13. you know what ruine it brought at laſt upon Abſalom and his party. It is ſtrange to obſerve how great miſeries and calamities befell both to Abimelech the ſon of Jerubbaal or Gideon, and likewiſe to the men of Shechem after that <hi>God had ſent an evil spirit</hi> of diviſion <hi>between them,</hi> Judg. 9. 23. they reſted not till they had contrived and effected each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers deſtruction.</p>
            <p>But unity and oneneſs in counſels doth uſually procure ſafety. We uſe to ſay <hi>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unita fortior,</hi> and it is a truth, Many arrows bound to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether are ſtrong, but being divided aſunder they are weak, and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily broken in pieces.</p>
            <p>I know that I am ſpeaking to ſuch worthy Perſons as are very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the bitter fruits of divided counſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls, no people in any age have been more diſturbed by factions and parties than we have been. Wherefore I humbly beg two Petitions of you, who are to be our Repreſentatives in this great Council.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That ye keep a full accord among your ſelves. <hi>Fall not out by the way,</hi> was the good advice of Joſeph to his brethren Gen. 45. 24.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119995:16"/> Satan and his inſtruments will do their utmoſt to divide you; watch therefore (I beſeech you) againſt all temptations in this kind, you cannot be too heedfull. The Apoſtle Paul giveth excellent counſel, which I alſo give unto you Rom. 16. 17. <hi>Mark them which cauſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and offences, and avoid them,</hi> have nothing to do with ſuch men.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That ye alſo hold a full correſpondence in your counſells with your brethren in the other nations that live under the ſame govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with you, and particularly with the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> (now ſo mercifully reſtored to their freedom,) and with thoſe that they ſhall leave in Government during the interval of Parliament. From them you have received eminent aſſiſtance in your national diſtreſs. O let it never be forgotten by you.</p>
            <p>The Iſlands of great <hi>Brittain</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> are like two bottles ſwimming in the water, if they claſh they break; or rather they are like a gallant ſhip and a ſmall boat floating in the Ocean, if they daſh one againſt the other by reaſon of winds and tempeſts, the boat is in great danger to be ſunk, or ſplit in pieces. Think not that you are able to ſtand alone; in taking advice with <hi>England</hi> will be your honour and ſafety, <hi>and a threefold cord is not eaſily broken,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerveth. Eccleſ. 4. 12.</p>
            <p>Some of you have already made a Covenant and league of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with them, with hands lifted up to the moſt high God, you muſt not onely vow, but <hi>pay your vows to God most high</hi> Pſal. 50. 14.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſpoken concerning the Qualifications of Counſellors that would ſave a Nation, I am now (in the ſecond place) to adde, That your Acts of counſel muſt alſo be ſuch as may ſave us from ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, and ſettle us in peace and ſafety.</p>
            <p>And herein I cannot, nor may undertake to direct your wiſdomes as to civil affairs, (that is not my work.) Ye are perſons that know the Laws of the Land, and the occaſions of the times, <hi>and what</hi> our <hi>Iſrael ought to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall onely mind you of my Maſters concernments, being now ſent with an Ambaſſage unto you from the Lord, and that is this.</p>
            <p>If ye deſire (as I doubt not but ye do,) to keep this great people from a fall, and to effect their ſafety; then your firſt and principal work muſt be to promote true Religion amongſt us.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119995:17"/>
            <p> If any ſhall ask, What Religion I mean? I ſay the reformed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, according to the written word of God. This is that Religion that hath been ſealed unto by ſo many famous martyrs and confeſſours; this is that Religion which ye all profeſs; this is that Religon which ye muſt ſeriouſly promote if ye intend to ſave this Iſland from deſtruction; upon this it is that the flouriſhng eſtate of the Commonwealth eſpecially dependeth. I ſhall make this plain unto you in three particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1 There is nothing will make a Nation ſo honourable, and full of ſplendor, as the maintaining and vigorous propagating of Religion will do. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> informeth us Rom: 9. 4. that <hi>the glory pertained to the Iſraelites.</hi> And why ſo? Becauſe they <hi>had the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God</hi> among them. The true worſhip and ſervice of God, whilſt it was upheld among them, made them the moſt glorious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the world. And on the otherſide when <hi>the Arke</hi> of God (before which God was ſerved and worſhiped) <hi>was taken</hi> by the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> then <hi>the glory departed from</hi> Iſrael 1. Sam. 4. 21. 22. The loſs of that did obſcure their glory and renown.</p>
            <p n="2">2 There is nothing can make a people ſo ſtrong and free from trouble, as the advanceing of Religion will do; no policie or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, or armies can do it. When the worſhip of God was ſettled at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> then <hi>God was known for a refuge</hi> there; and <hi>the Kings</hi> that intended to invade the country <hi>ſaw it and marvailed, and fear took hold upon them, and pain as of a woman in travail,</hi> Pſal. 48. 1-6 <hi>The ſanctuary</hi> of God among the <hi>Iſraelites was the excellency of their ſtrength,</hi> Ezek. 24. 21. This is the bulwarks of a Nation:</p>
            <p n="3">3 There is nothing can make the land ſo proſperous and plenteous in all ſorts of outward bleſſings as this will do, if Religion be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in its purity. When <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> had reformed Religion after a great apoſtaſie, and had advanced it to its former glory and luſtre, it is ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. Chron. 17. 5. that <hi>all</hi> Judah <hi>brought him preſents and he had riches and honour in abundance.</hi> This was it that made him pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous. So likewiſe it is ſaid concerning <hi>Obed edom,</hi> that <hi>the Lord bleſsed the houſe of</hi> Obed edom <hi>and all that pertained to him becauſe of the Arke of God,</hi> that abode in his houſe for a time, as you may read 2. Sam. 6. 12.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:119995:17"/>
            <p> Now to the intent that Religion may he advanced and propagated throughout this Land, give me leave humbly to propoſe two things. 1 Remove that which may hinder the growth and glory of our Religion. 2 Do thoſe things which may promote and advance it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If ye would have the Goſpel to proſper, and Religion to flouriſh, then endeavour to your utmoſt ſtrength and power to take thoſe evils out of the way that may keep it under, and obſtruct its growth, beauty, and glory. I will name ſome of thoſe impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Popery</hi> together <hi>with all its appurtenances,</hi> doth much hinder the progreſs of the glorious Goſpel in this Land. As the Pope is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: ſo his doctrine, worſhip, and Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are oppoſite to that doctrine, worſhip and diſcipline which Chriſt would have to be eſtabliſhed in his Church. Popery is deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the Proteſtant Religion. Sathan, <hi>the angel of the bottomleſs pit,</hi> who is <hi>King</hi> over the Papiſts, <hi>hath his name in the Hebrew tongue Abaddon, and in the Greek tongue Apollyon,</hi> i. e. A deſtroyer Rev. 9. 11. He doth what he can by his ſeminary Prieſts and Jeſuites to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy our Religion with all the profeſſors of it.</p>
            <p>May it (therefore) be the ſpecial care of you our Worthies to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate Popery with all that pertaineth to it out of this Land: And to that end to command; That thoſe good Laws already in force againſt Prieſts and Jeſuites may be put into execution; That Papiſts and their children may be enjoyned to attend upon the publique worſhip of God in our Congregations; and That where any defect ſhall be found in the Laws (as to this matter) it may be amended for the time to come.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Our Religion groaneth under that <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Separation</hi> that hath been made from the Church of Chriſt in this land, and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thoſe many Sects, Errours, and Hereſies that have iſſued from thence, the remembrances whereof remain written in tears and blood in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> It may be ſaid of theſe Errours in general, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letus</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 17. that they <hi>eat as the canker</hi> or gangren, inſomuch as the very heart of our religion is almoſt torn out by them</p>
            <p>May ye (therefore) be pleaſed to uſe your utmoſt endeavours for the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119995:18"/> ſuppreſſion of them all, and of that which is the fountain of them all, namely the Separate Congregations in the Land. Both root and branch muſt be taken away if ye intend to have Religion to flouriſh.</p>
            <p>Yet would I be rightly underſtood herein. I mean not that I would have any godly perſons interrupted in their meeting together to pray, or confer about the things pertaining to the kingdom of God; ſo as care be taken that none do plot or contrive miſchief a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Government under which they live, by pretence of thoſe meetings, as ſome have too leudly done. But I deſire this, That none be permitted to gather Churches (as they call them) out of our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Congregations, or to exerciſe acts pertaining to Church-government in any of their private meetings.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Prophanneſs</hi> of all ſorts doth exceedingly hinder the flouriſhing eſtate of Religion in this Iſland, never were greater abominations committed in a land of light, than among us, which may juſtly cauſe the Lord to depart from his ſanctuary, and to abhor us.</p>
            <p>May the Lord (therefore) be pleaſed to work up your hearts to an unfeigned hatred of all prophanneſs and ungodlineſs whatſoever, and to uſe all good means to purge it out of the land. And to that end I beg; That all Magiſtrates in their ſeveral capacities may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to put the Laws made againſt groſs ſins into due execution, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially thoſe that relate to the puniſhment of that general ſin, the prophanation of the Lords day; and That further proviſions may be made againſt groſs offences, where the Laws are defective.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If ye would have true Religion to thrive and flouriſh, then ye muſt alſo ſet upon the doing of thoſe things which may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and advance Religion. I will inſtance onely in five things which (if done) would magnify our Religion, wherein I become your moſt humble Petitioner in Chriſts ſtead.</p>
            <p n="1">1 There is nothing can exalt Religion ſo much as <hi>a godly, learned, orthodox and painful Miniſtry.</hi> It is ſaid of good King Jehoſhaphat 2 Chron. 17. 6. that <hi>his heart was lift up in the ways of God.</hi> As if the Holy Ghoſt had ſaid thus of him, He did moſt zealouſly ſeek to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and advance the true religion of God. But what courſe took he to advance it? That you ſhall ſee in the three next verſes. He provided carefully that all his people might be taught and inſtructed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119995:18"/> in Religion, he ſent teaching Levites and able Miniſters into all parts of the land, and Magiſtrates alſo with them to protect and encourage them in their Miniſtry. And it is ſaid of King Joſiah, that <hi>he encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged the Priests and Levites to the ſervice of the houſe of the Lord,</hi> 2 Chron. 35. 2, 3. That was the way he made uſe of for the ſettling of Religion.</p>
            <p>Therefore I intreat, That perſons unordained to that great work, and who deſpiſe that great Ordinance of Chriſt, may not be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into any Miniſterial employment in this Church and Nation; That ſuch Miniſters ordained as are ignorant, ſcandalous, or unſound in judgment in the fundamentals of Religion, may not be admitted to any paſtoral charge in the Land; That thoſe who are already crept in may upon due proof be ſuſpended from their places, and in caſe they reform not, ejected; That all good endeavours be uſed to ſtore every congregation with ſuch a ſoul-ſaving Preacher, as may ſeed them with knowledg and underſtanding; And That timous care may be taken to encourage ſuch Miniſters, leaſt themſelves and their families ſtarve for want of outward neceſſaries, whilſt they deal forth their ſpirituals to others.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſettlement and due adminiſtration of that <hi>Diſcipline</hi> or <hi>Cburch-Government</hi> which Chriſt hath appointed to be in his Church, is of ſingular uſe to pluck up the weeds that the wheat may flouriſh. This is that <hi>fence of Gods vineyard</hi> ſpoken of Iſa. 5. 2. that ſerveth both to keep in the godly, and to keep out the ungodly. The want of this holy diſcipline is a great ground of lamentation.</p>
            <p>Herein I intreat; That, foraſmuch as the matters of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment are of ſo great weight and importance, ye would pleaſe therein to walk hand in hand with our Brethren in the other parts of theſe Dominions, and That all ſuch matters may be concluded of by a Synodical Aſſembly of the three Nations.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The due <hi>adminiſtration</hi> of all <hi>Chriſts</hi> holy <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions makes much to the flouriſhing condition of Religion in the Land, eſpecially of thoſe that are the ſealing Ordinances; and the miſuſage or non-uſage of thoſe Ordinances is our great reproach in all the reformed Churches. Theſe are the food of our ſouls.</p>
            <p>I therefore pray; That all ſuch Miniſters as have the care of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119995:19"/> may be required to adminiſter all Chriſts Ordinances, even the ſealing Ordinances to duly qualified perſons within their precincts, though as yet the Government of the Church be not ſetled. Methinks it is ſad that any of the Lords people ſhould be deprived of their ſpiritual food, and ſo famiſh, whilſt we are contending which is the beſt way of carving it out unto them; And That none be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to adminiſter any of the ſealing Ordinances ſave in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes whereof they are Paſtors, unleſs it be by the conſent of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in whoſe Pariſh they deſire to adminiſter them.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Catechiſing</hi> in the principles of Religion is alſo an excellent way and mean to propagate Religion and cauſe it to flouriſh. This is, milk for babes in Chriſt. And it is for want of the due performance of this, by Miniſters, Parents, and Maſters of Families, that there is ſo little found knowledge and underſtanding in the Land.</p>
            <p>My requeſt therefore is, That ye will by all due ways and means ſhew your approbation of the way of Catechiſing, and That ye will (as ye have opportunity,) ſtir up all ſorts of perſons in their ſeveral places to a conſciencious performance of their duty therein.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Laſtly. <hi>Schools of Learning</hi> do alſo contribute much to the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing ſtate of Religion. Thoſe are the nurſeries wherein grow up many plants for the uſe both of Church, and Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>May you therefore pleaſe to take this alſo into your ſerious thoughts, and to provide That the Univerſity near this City, and all ſuch Schools as are already erected and founded, may be nouriſhed and maintained; That fit Schoolmaſters may be provided and well encouraged; and That other Schools may alſo be erected as occaſion ſhall require.</p>
            <p>Theſe things (amongſt many others that might have been menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned) I have been bold to mind you of from the Lord, that ſo by your counſells ye may prove to be the bleſſed Phyſicians of this lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Church and Nation.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with that ſpeech of <hi>David</hi> to his ſonne <hi>Solomon</hi> when he was to build the houſe of the Lord, 1 Chron. 22. 16. <hi>Ariſe therefore, and be doing, and the Lord be with you.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119995:19"/>
            <head>The Second Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Jude verſe 19.</bibl>
               <q>Theſe be they who ſeparate themſelves, ſenſual, having not the Spirit.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat it is a duty appertaining to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel to preach the Word of God ſoundly and ſincerely, <hi>in doctrine ſhewing incorruptneſs,</hi> is a thing that none will deny. It is commanded that they uſe <hi>ſound speech that cannot be condemned,</hi> Tit. 2. 8, 9.</p>
            <p>But that is not all that Miniſters have to do; they ſtand bound alſo to preach ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Truths, otherwiſe they ſhall be found wanting in their duty toward the people of God. We are informed that the right timing of a thing is that which ſetteth a luſtre upon it, Eccl. 3. 11. <hi>Every thing is beautiful in its time;</hi> fruit is the beſt when it is ripe; words though they may be truths, yet loſe their beauty if unſeaſonably ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. And therefore Solomon hath an excellent Proverb for this Prov. 25. 11. <hi>A word fitly spoken</hi> (or <hi>upon its wheels,</hi> (as it is in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119995:20"/> margine,) with a due concurrence and obſervation of all its circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,) <hi>Is like apples of gold in pictures of ſilver,</hi> pleaſant as apples, profitable as gold and ſilver. When the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> obſerved the giddy humours of Sectaries, Apoſtates from the faith which once they had profeſſed, he makes this the work of that time by all good means to confirm the Saints in the truth againſt thoſe phantaſies, and to that end writeth an Epiſtle to them (1 Pet. 5. 12.) <hi>Exhorting and teſtifying that this is the true grace of God wherein they stand.</hi> So when <hi>Paul</hi> obſerved that <hi>the City</hi> of <hi>Athens was wholly given to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry,</hi> he bendeth himſelf to this ſeaſonable doctrine, even to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare</hi> to them <hi>that God whom they did ignorantly worſhip,</hi> Act. 16. 23. Miniſters muſt preach ſuch points as may be of moſt uſe for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>Now the ſpecial work upon Faſting dayes is to humble the ſoul for ſin. God requireth that <hi>on the tenth day of the ſecond month</hi> which was the aniverſary day of humiliation to <hi>Iſrael, they ſhould afflict their ſouls</hi> Lev. 16 29. 31; and threatneth Chap. 23 29 that, <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſoul it ſhall be that ſhall not be afflicted on that ſame day, ſhall be cut off from among his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it is that the word of God ought to be preached upon the Faſting day, that ſo the people may be brought to ſound repentance and humiliation for ſin, and ſo made more fervent in their ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to God for pardon; As appeareth by that direction the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> giveth to <hi>Baruch</hi> Jer. 36. 6. 7. <hi>Go thou</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and read in the roll which thou haſt written from my mouth the words of the Lord in the ears of the people in the Lords houſe upon the Faſting day; it may be they will preſent their ſupplication before the Lord, and turn every one from his evil way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how ſhould we mourn for our ſins unleſs we know them? That which brought <hi>David</hi> to true ſorrow and heart breaking for his ſin was the certain knowledge he had of his own ſinful condition, <hi>I know,</hi> or acknowledge <hi>my tranſgreſſions</hi> (ſaith he Pſal. 51. 3.) <hi>and my ſin is ever before me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how ſhould we know our ſins ſo as to mourn for them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Gods Miniſters do their endeavours to diſcover them to us? <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> (of whom mention was made before) never repented or mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119995:20"/> for his ſins of Adultery and Murder until <hi>Nathan the Prophet came unto him,</hi> and took pains with him in the diſcovery of them, as is clear Pſal. 51. title; you may read the whole hiſtory a Sam. Cap. 12. To this end it is that the Lord calleth upon every one of us who are his Heralds Iſa. 58. 1. <hi>Cry aloud, ſpare not, lift up thy voice like a trumpet, and ſhew my people their tranſgreſſions, and the houſe of</hi> Jacob <hi>their ſins.</hi> This alone is the uſual way that God taketh for the diſcovery of ſin.</p>
            <p>Yet to make an exact and particular diſcovery of ſin, is a thing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together impoſſible to be done by any Miniſter in the world. For <hi>who can know his</hi> own <hi>errours,</hi> Pſal. 19. 12. how much leſs the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours that other men are overtaken with? Wherefore the Miniſters of Chriſt have uſed to do in this caſe of the diſcovery of ſin, as he that draweth the Land-skip of a Country or Kingdom, who becauſe he cannot deſcribe every buſh, or tree, or houſe, doth therefore take notice onely of the moſt eminent cities, and towns, and rivers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. <hi>Nathan</hi> takes notice of <hi>Davids</hi> great ſpots &amp; ſtains onely, 2 Sam. 12. 9. <hi>Thou haſt killed</hi> Uriah <hi>the</hi> Hittite <hi>with the ſword, and haſt taken his wife to be thy wife;</hi> he ſpeaketh of his great ſins. So the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in their diſcovery of ſin take notice of the fouleſt, as of <hi>Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude againſt God, Hypocriſy, Covetouſneſs, Murder, Drunkenneſs, Idolatry, Lying, Pride, Contempt of Gods word, Security in ſinning,</hi> and the like. The greateſt ſins are eſpecially to be taken notice of.</p>
            <p>Upon this account (that I may diſcharge my duty aright upon this our Faſting day,) I have ſingled out the ſin of Separation, as the fouleſt ſin of this age, and generation, and therefore moſt ſeaſonable to be ſpoken of that we may be humbled before the Lord our God.</p>
            <p>I know indeed that it is the part of the Lords meſſengers to cry out againſt, and to endeavour to bring others unto a godly ſorrow for all the abominations of the Land, for all that groſs ignorance, ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and damnable prophanneſs that is riſe amongſt us. And I doubt not but my brethren that are to beat a part in the work of this day, will endeavour to acknowledge all our iniquities, and tranſgreſſions before the Lord, and wreſtle with the Lord for the pardon of them.</p>
            <p>But I muſt ingenuouſly profeſs that I conceive the ſin of Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be the Achan, the great abomination of theſe Lands, upon
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119995:21"/> diverſe accounts, of which I ſhall ſpeak anon, and therefore moſt to be laid to heart by the Lords people this day; To which end I have made choice of this Text, <hi>Theſe are they who ſeparate themſelves,</hi> &amp;c. And before I proceed any further, I muſt firſt ſhew the depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of theſe words upon thoſe that go before.</p>
            <p>The ſubject matter of this Epiſtle is a vehement exhortation of the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> to all the godly in all ages; That they <hi>contend earneſtly for the faith which was once committed to the Saints,</hi> as you ſee in the third Verſe; and That they ſuffer not themſelves to be drawn from the faith and belief of the Goſpel by thoſe falſe teachers who were <hi>crept in</hi> among them <hi>unawares</hi> in the fourth Verſe.</p>
            <p>The arguments by which the Apoſtle perſuadeth with theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers to beware of theſe ſeducers are of two ſorts,</p>
            <p n="1">I He argueth from the puniſhments that the Lord hath inflicted upon thoſe ſins to which theſe falſe teachers endeavoured to ſeduce them; which judgments he layeth down before them in three ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Of the deſtruction of the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for their unbelief, in the fifth Verſe.</item>
               <item>2 Of the everlaſting ruine of the reprobate Angels for their pride, in the ſixth Verſe.</item>
               <item>3 Of the vengeance of God upon <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha</hi> for their fornication and buggery, in the ſeventh Verſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">II He alſo argueth from the perſonal vices that raigned in theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers, Whence it was altogether unfit that they ſhould be leaders of theſe believers, and alſo unſafe that theſe believers ſhould be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of them.</p>
            <p>The ſins that theſe ſeducers were guilty of, are reckoned up under thirteen heads in this Epiſtle; two of them are compriſed in this Verſe, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Schiſme, they were ſuch as made a rent in, and ſeparation from the Church of God, that is laid down in theſe words, <hi>Theſe are they who ſeparate themſelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 Steering their courſe by ſenſe, and carnal reaſon and not by the Spirit of God, in theſe words, <hi>Senſual having not the ſpirit.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119995:21"/>
            <p> Mine intention is to ſpeak of the firſt of the ſins mentioned in this Verſe, to which theſe falſe Teachers were addicted, and which did evidence them to be ſeducers, they were ſuch as did <hi>ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> from the Church and people of God.</p>
            <p>Where it is to be noted how the Apoſtle pointeth them out as it were with the finger, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. As if he ſhould have ſaid thus, Behold, obſerve, and mark theſe men to be vile and pernicious perſons; for they do willingly cut themſelves off from communion with the Church of God. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as <hi>Eſtius</hi> noteth upon the Text) ſignifieth to lead or allure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bounds of the Church, to break the pale thereof; A term which I am not aſhamed to uſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though it have been much flouted a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of late. Theſe are they that ſingle and ſeparate themſelves from the Church, making parties and factions therein, and drawing into ſect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> among themſelves, obſerve avoid them.</p>
            <p>Now whereas the the Apoſtle reckoneth up this for one of thoſe great ſins that theſe falſe teachers were guilty of, that they did ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate themſelves from the Church of God. You may obſerve,</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That there is a Separation that hath been an old errour, even in ſome men that have pretended to be knowing and religious men, and have undertaken to be leaders and teachers of others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee the doctrine to be clearly grounded upon the Text, Theſe perſons Jude ſpeaketh of were ſuch as pretended to be ſo full of knowledg and piety, that they undertook to be guides to theſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and again theſe Chriſtians looked upon them as meet for ſuch an employment, ſo as the Apoſtle is neceſſitated to write unto them to admoniſh them that they be not ſeduced by them; and yet though they pretended to ſo much, they were guilty of Separation, this was one of the great faults they were inclined unto.</p>
            <p>I muſt acknowledg that this point (although it be a plain truth ariſing naturally from the Text) may ſeem to ſome to be a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet point to be inſiſted upon in ſuch an age as this is, and eſpecially at a publique Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, and before ſuch an honorably Aſſembly as is now gathered together.</p>
            <p>But I muſt profeſs that I judg the ſin of Separation to be the great ſin of our times (as I ſaid before) and that therefore I am bound to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119995:22"/> give mine open teſtimony againſt it here in this publique Aſſembly, as well as I have done in mine own more private Congregation in the worſt of times; which I ſpeak not (God is my witneſs) out of any vain oſtentation (for I have nothing to glory in, ſave in the croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt) but that I may withhold an occaſion from them that ſhall ſeek occaſion of offence at this doctrine.</p>
            <p>And becauſe I know (and ſhall prove) that there is a Separation, even amongſt us, that is a great ſin, therefore I am convinced that it is my duty to ſpeak of it upon this our day of Humiliation, and that no time is more ſeaſonable than this.</p>
            <p>Yet in treating upon this point, I reſolve (the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt aſſiſting) to uſe all circumſpection and caution, and to ſpeak nothing but by plain proof of Scripture. And therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">1 I reſolve that I will not willingly uſe any ſharp or bitter refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions upon any that I hope do truly fear God, ſo as juſtly to grieve them. I know it is a foul fault to <hi>make the heart of the rightous ſad, whom the Lord hath not made ſad</hi> Ezek. 13. 22. which is done by ſpeaking <hi>lies,</hi> and not by ſpeaking plain Scripture truths. For to the godly every word of God is ſweet, yea <hi>it is the joy and rejoycing of their hearts,</hi> as Jeremiah ſpeaketh Chap. 15. 16.</p>
            <p n="2">2 I ſhall in my diſcourſe deſign the information of miſtaken judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, rather than the dirt-daubing or beſpattering of thoſe that differ in judgment from me; and that I am ſure is a duty commanded Gal. 6. 1. <hi>Brethren if a man be overtaken in a fault, ye which are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, restore ſuch an one in the spirit of meekneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 I will not gratify wicked, prophane and ſuperſtitious men by any thing that I ſhall ſpeak unto this point. For that would be a great ſin <hi>to ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked, that he ſhould not return from his wicked way by promiſing him life,</hi> as the Lord ſpeaketh Ezek. 13. 22. I profeſs to hate prophanneſs and ſuperſtition on the one ſide, as I do ſinfull Separation on the other ſide.</p>
            <p>That therefore I may duly qualify that which I am to ſpeak at this time, it muſt be known and remembred, that I condemn not all Separation as ſinfull, I ſaid, <hi>There is a ſeparation that is an errour,</hi> not that all kind of Separation is erroneous. For there is a lawfull and holy Separation, and an unlawfull and unholy Separation, there is a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119995:22"/> Separation commanded in the Word of God, and there is a Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion forbidden in the ſame Word.</p>
            <p>And it will be needfull, and I hope profitable to ſpeak of both theſe, to the intent, That thoſe who decry and ſpeak againſt all the people of the Lord under the name of Sectaries, Schiſmaticks and Separatiſts may be convinced of their fault, and humbled for their miſcarriage in their raſh cenſuring and nick-naming of thoſe that are ſound and orthodox in their judgments; and That thoſe who are guilty of this ſin indeed may be informed in their judgments, and (if the will of God be ſo) may alſo be reformed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, There is then a lawfull Separation, and holy Separatiſt. Such were the Nazarites mentioned Numb. 6. 1. <hi>Speak unto the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael, and ſay unto them</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>when either man or woman ſhall ſeparate themſelves to vow a vow of a Nazarite, to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate themſelves unto the Lord, he ſhall ſeparate himſelf from wine &amp;c.</hi> And they were called Nazarites of Nazar, <hi>ſeparavit,</hi> becauſe they were ſeparated from worldly occaſions, and devoted and ſanctified to the Lord. Thus all thoſe that are baptized into the name of Chriſt are by profeſſion Separatiſts, that is, they are <hi>ſeparated from ſin, the world and the devil</hi> to the uſe and ſervice of God onely; and they ought ſo to walk as thoſe that are <hi>dead to ſin, but alive to God</hi> through Jeſus Chriſt. And as baptized perſons are by their ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm declared to be ſeparated and ſet apart to God, ſo we are all bound to judg them to be Gods, and to have full right to all Church mercies whileſt they continue in that good profeſſion. This was Pauls judgment Gal. 3. 27. <hi>As many of you as have been baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea there is a Separation ſtrictly commanded of God, and to be made by all the godly, as appeareth by many Scriptures of the old and new Teſtament; of which theſe are the chief, Iſa. 52. 11. <hi>Depart ye, depart ye, go ye out from thence, touch no unclean thing, go ye out of the midſt of her.</hi> And Jer. 15. 19. <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord, If thou return then will I bring thee again, and thou ſhalt ſtand before me, and if thou take forth the precious from the vile, thou ſhalt be as my mouth, let them return unto thee, but return not thou unto them.</hi> And 2 Cor. 6. 17. <hi>Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye ſeparate ſaith</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:119995:23"/> 
               <hi>the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing.</hi> And 2 Theſ. 3. 6. <hi>Now we command you brethren in the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye withdraw your ſelves from every brother that walketh diſorderly, and not after the traditions which he received from us.</hi> And Revel. 18. 4. <hi>Come out of her my people.</hi> I have mentioned all theſe Scriptures together, that you may obſerve the harmonious conſent of Gods holy Word for an holy Separation; what is intended in them will be opened unto you as we go on in our diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Now this Separation commanded, and by all the godly to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavored, I ſhall lay down particularly and diſtinctly in ſeven things.</p>
            <p n="1">I The Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt muſt in their preaching make a ſeparation, or put a difference between <hi>the precious and the vile,</hi> between the godly and the ungodly, by confirming and comforting the one, and by reproving and threatning the other. In the pureſt Churches there is chaff aſwell as wheat, droſs aſwell as gold; and that man that undertaketh the calling of the Miniſtry, and yet hath not learned to make this diſtinction, can hardly be judged a <hi>Teacher ſent from God.</hi> This, this (I ſay) is that <hi>taking forth</hi> (or ſeparating) <hi>the precious from the vile,</hi> which the Lord giveth in commandment to the Prophet Jeremiah in that place before quoted Chap. 15. 19. And they that ground their gathering of Churches out of Churches upon this ſcripture (as many do) do ſqueez bloud out of the Text inſtead of ſincere milk; as will appear by theſe three conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1 From the words conjoyned in the Text, which are theſe, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, if thou return, then will I bring thee again, and thou ſhalt ſtand before me; and if thou take the precious from the vile thou ſhalt be as my mouth; let them return unto thee, but return not thou unto them.</hi> Theſe words are ſpoken unto Jeremiah who was one of the Lords prophets, employed in delivering his meſſage to the Church of the Jews eſpecially; the native ſenſe and meaning of this enunciation of the Lord to him is thus much. If thou caſt off all thy diſtruſtfulneſs, impatiencie and grudging againſt me, whereunto thou art inclinable, and turneſt unto me, relying upon me by faith, and walking in a conſtant courſe of obedience, then I will ſtrengthen thee (as in times paſt) and give thee grace to attend upon my ſervice freely without any fear or diſtractedneſs. And if thou doſt faithfully
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119995:23"/> and conſtantly (without fear of man or flattery of any) declare what the true good is which I approve of, and the evil which I diſlike; if thou countenanceſt that that is good, and doſt bear up and comfort good men and contrariwiſe condemneſt that which is evil, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt down wicked men, then thou ſhalt ſhew by theſe effects that thou art my true prophet, that thou ſpeakeſt in thy Miniſtry as the Oracle of God So as its clear that this taking forth of the precious from the vile was an act appertaining to his miniſterial Office in dividing the Word of God aright to the comfort of the godly and terrour of the ungodly, and not in gathering a particular Church out of the natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Church of the Jews, and unchurching the reſt of the people.</p>
            <p n="2">2 We find it no where recorded in the holy Scriptures that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> did any ſuch thing, as to take any out of the Church of the Jews, and joyn them into a ſeparate Church or ſociety a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves. And certainly if it had been the Lords intention that in that great defection and backſliding of the Church of the Jews, the Prophet ſhould have gathered a ſelect number out of them into a particular Church fellowſhip amongſt themſelves, there would have been ſome footſteps of his actings in that kind, eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that it was ſo new, rare, and ſtrange a work.</p>
            <p n="3">3 If the Prophet had attempted to have done ſuch a thing he had without doubt ſinned therein, and ſo had not been as Gods mouth, but muſt have been numbred among the falſe Prophets. For he had therein tranſgreſſed by digreſſing from the practiſe of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, who was born in as corrupt a time of the Church as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> lived in, and yet he made no rent nor ſeparation among them, but held communion with them in all the Ordinances, and Inſtitutions of the Lord, kept the holy Sabbath with them in their Synagogues, obſerved the Paſsover with them, waited at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> during the time of their ſolemn Feaſts, doing all things in Church fellowſhip wirh them, as is abundantly manifeſt in the Hiſtories of the Evangeliſts. So that you ſee that this word of the Lord to <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> intended not any ſuch ſeparation as ſome would infer from it, but onely the putting of a diſtinction in his preaching between the godly and the ungodly.</p>
            <p>But this taking forth the precious from the vile, putting a deſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119995:24"/> between the holy, and the wicked, in preaching comfortable doctrine to the children of God, and terrour to the children of the devil, is a duty belonging to every faithful Miniſter of Chriſt; and if Gods meſſengers do not obſerve this diſtinction they <hi>give that which is holy to dogs, and caſt</hi> their <hi>pearls before ſwine,</hi> which is a thing utterly forbidden them to do Mat. 7. 6.</p>
            <p n="2">II All the people of God muſt ſeparate from communion with Idolaters in the worſhip and ſervice of God. This is a duty frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoyned in the word of God. And this ſeparation muſt be two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</p>
            <p n="1">1 From that worſhip that heathens give to their falſe Gods, unto idols; which is forbidden in the firſt Commandment. This is that which is eſpecially intended in the 52. of Iſaiah. Verſe. 11. before cited, where the Lord enjoyneth his people to <hi>depart, and go out</hi> from <hi>Babilon,</hi> and to <hi>touch no unclean thing</hi> that they did or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in the ſervice of their idols. We muſt ſeparate from all idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in their idolatrous worſhip, for it is written, Mat. 4. 10. <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> All di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine honour both that that is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>worſhip,</hi> and that which is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſervice,</hi> belongeth unto the Lord our God onely, and therefore we may not meddle with idolaters, not with their idols.</p>
            <p n="2">2 From the falſe and idolatrous worſhip of the true God, ſuch as the Papiſts perform to God by their images and ceremonies. Of this kind of Separation it is that the Lord ſpeaketh Revel. 18. 4. before mentioned. <hi>Come out of her my people,</hi> that is, Separate from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal juriſdiction which is the ſpiritual Babilon, under which the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God have been in as great ſpiritual captivity and ſlavery, as ever the Church of the Jews were under in Caldea, or all Iſrael in Egypt. And there are two reaſons rendered there why we muſt thus ſeparate.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Becauſe unleſs we ſeparate from the idolatrous worſhip of the Papiſts, we ſhall certainly be partakers of the ſins which they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit in that worſhip, <hi>That ye be not partakers of her ſins.</hi> It is a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity for a man to think that he can be preſent at a Maſs, or other worſhip that they do, and yet keep his heart to God, and not ſin
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119995:24"/> therein; preſence at idol-worſhip voluntarily, maketh a man to be partaker in the ſin of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Becauſe, If we do not thus come out, all thoſe intollerable miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that ſhall come inevitably upon theſe idolaters ſhall light upon us likewiſe, <hi>and that ye receive not of her plagues.</hi> Thoſe that will needs ſin together muſt alſo ſuffer together, this is a juſt and righteous thing with God.</p>
            <p>Both theſe reaſons ſhould mightily prevail with us to hate idolatry and to avoid and ſeparate from them that are idolaters in that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice they pretend to do to God. And this is the ſecond branch of lawfull Separation.</p>
            <p n="3">III The godly muſt ſeparate from all conjugal ſociety with ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, they may not contract marriage with them at all. This is that ſeparation ſpoken of Ezra Chap. 10. 11. <hi>Separate your ſelves from the people of the land,</hi> and <hi>from the strange wives;</hi> and alſo Deut. 7. 3. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make marriages with them, thy daughter thou ſhalt not give unto his ſon, nor his daughter ſhalt thou take unto thy ſon.</hi> Of this kind of Separation it is that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh in the 2. Cor. 6. 17. if you compare it with the verſes precedent. <hi>Be ye not unequal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yoaked with unbeleevers—Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye ſeparate ſaith the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is utterly unlawful for the true worſhippers of God to ſoder in affinity with ſuch as are idolaters; for them that profeſs the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant religion to marry with heathens, or with Papiſts.</p>
            <p>Yet this that I ſay in this matter is to be underſtood with thoſe Cautions that the Apoſtle giveth in this caſe, 1 Cor. 7. 10-15. For if it be ſo that any one that is a beleever hath contracted marriage with one that is an unbeleever or heathen, this difference of religion is not a ſufficient cauſe of divorce or ſeparation in the dayes of the Goſpel. Though it be a ſin to marry with them of a falſe religion, and ſo a juſt cauſe of humiliation, yet after marriage this is not a juſt ground for a divorce.</p>
            <p n="4">IIII It is a duty appertaining to the ſervants of God to ſeparate themſelves from the unneceſſary civil ſociety of all wicked men, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of all ſuch as walk and act in an ungodly manner. This was <hi>Jacobs</hi> care Gen. 49. 6. <hi>O my ſoul come not thou into their ſecret, unto</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:119995:25"/> 
               <hi>their aſſembly, mine honour be not thou united.</hi> He reſolveth to have nothing to do unneceſſarily with cruel and mercileſs men though they were his near relations. If godly men come into ungodly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany without good occaſion ſo to do, they may ruine themſelves thereby, For <hi>Solomon</hi> informeth us Prov. 13. 20. <hi>that a companion of fools ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a moſt certain truth that the godly may come into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of ſuch as are moſt wicked and prophane, and converſe with them upon juſt occaſions, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 If neceſſary civil affairs whether publique or private do call for it. The Apoſtle forbiddeth not to forbear <hi>company altogether with fornicators, or covetous, or extortioners, or idolaters, for then we muſt needs go out of the world,</hi> 1 Cor. 5. 10. Doubtleſs it is lawful for any good Chriſtian, whether Miniſter or other to converſe with the worſt of men upon a neceſſary civil account, and none ought to paſs a raſh judgment againſt his neighbour for ſo doing.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If a beleever have any cauſe to hope that he may win another to God, or to the love of religion by companying with him, he may alſo company with him lawfully upon that account. Of this the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh 1 Pet. 2. 12. <hi>Having your converſation honeſt among the Gentiles, that whereas they speak againſt you, as evil doers they may by your good works which they ſhall behold glorify God in the day of their viſitation.</hi> You ſee then that it is lawful and convenient for the godly upon ſome occaſions to converſe with the worſt of men. But if ſuch like ſpecial occaſions do not intervene, then the company of the ungodly muſt be quite forborn, and a ſeparation made from their ſociety; which is the fourth branch of an holy and lawful Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration.</p>
            <p n="5">V When the children of God have a juſt cauſe to be in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of ungodly men, they muſt always be ſure of this that they do Separate from their wicked courſes; they muſt hold no eommunion with them in their ſins though they do converſe with them; that is a thing utterly unlawful. It is a thing abſolutely required of all beleevers, 1 Tim. 5. 12. that they <hi>be not partakers with other mens ſins.</hi> A man truely gracious will let ſuch a watch over himſelf when he is neceſſitated to be among ungodly men that he will not give the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119995:25"/> leaſt approbation or countenance to any of their lewd and ungraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous courſes; and it is a great ſin to keep them company when they are acting their wicked prancks. This the godly are oft adviſed to beware, Prov. 23. 20. <hi>Be not among wine-bibbers, among riotous eaters of fleſh.</hi> Come not among them when they are committing their ſins, meddle not with them in their drunkenneſs and gluttony. We muſt ever be ſuch Separatiſts.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. The godly may and muſt ſeparate from the pollutions of any Church they live in. It is one thing to ſeparate from the Church of God, and another to ſeparate from the defilements that are in the Church. If that a Church be corrupted, ſo as any of Gods Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be broken, and his ſtanding rules tranſgreſſed and ſwerved from, it concerneth all godly men to take heed to themſelves that they be not alſo defiled. A notable pattern and example of this we have in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf. It was one of Gods ſtatute Laws concerning the Paſſeover that it ſhould be kept every year on the fourteenth day of the firſt month at even, as you may ſee in its firſt inſtitution Exod. 12. 6. <hi>Ye ſhall keep up the</hi> (paſchal) <hi>Lamb until the fourteenth day of the ſame</hi> (that is to ſay of the <hi>first</hi> Verſe 2.) <hi>month, and the whole aſsembly of the congregation of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall kill it in the evening;</hi> And ſo the Lord ſpeaketh expreſly Levit. 23. 5. <hi>In the fourteenth day of the firſt month at even is the Lords paſſeover.</hi> But the Church of the Jews did tranſgreſs this in regard of the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time. For they had made it a tradition among them that when the Paſſeover fell upon the evening before their ordinary Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, they did put off the keeping of the Paſſeover unto the Sabbath day, and ſo kept the Paſſeover upon their ordinary Sabbath, perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both duties under one. Thus it fell out in that year wherein our Lord was crucified, as appeareth by comparing Mat. 26. 20. with Mar. 15. 42. and John 18. 28. where you may note that the Jews kept the Paſſeover that evening the Lord Jeſus was crucified, at which time began their ordinary ſabbath. Yet the Lord Jeſus (who held cloſe communion with the Church of the Jews) declineth their practiſe in that very circumſtance of time in which they failed, and obſerveth the Paſſeover in its proper ſeaſon appointed by the Lord; and this is carefully obſerved by the Evangeliſts Mat. 26. 20. <hi>Now</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:119995:26"/> 
               <hi>when the evening was come he ſate down with the twelve;</hi> And Luk. 22. 14. <hi>And when the hour was come he ſare down &amp;c.</hi> He would not fail in the very time of this Ordinance though a whole Church di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed from it.</p>
            <p>Though Chriſtians are bound to hold communion with the Church in which they live, ſo far as they walk up to the rule, yet in any pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution that is in that Church, they need not, nor ought to be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers; and ſuch a frame of ſpirit doth well become every Chriſtian. This therefore juſtifieth the practiſe of ſuch as flie from the errours that are in the Church, not daring to meddle with any impoſitions which are not of the Lords appointment therein, though they may not, nor dare ſeparate from her.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Laſtly, After due admonition given to ſcandalous ſinners who live in the Church, if the admonition be rejected, and the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners prove obſtinate, the Church muſt ſeparate them, and caſt them out from her communion. This leſſon our Lord Jeſus teacheth Mat. 18. 15-17. <hi>If thy brother ſhall treſpaſs againſt thee, go and tell him his fault between thee and him, if he ſhall hear thee thou hast gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy brother, But if he will not hear thee then take with thee one or two more, that in the mouth of two or three witneſſes, every word may be eſtabliſhed, And if he ſhall neglect to hear them, tell it unto the Church; but if he neglect to hear the Church, let him be unto thee as an heathen man and a publican.</hi> In which Text our Saviour doth not teach a Non-communion as ſome call it, viz. that when we ſee Church members to offend, and there is in the Church no help to be found for the redreſs thereof, we muſt therefore decline communion with that Church immediately; but he teacheth an Excommunion, viz. that ſuch as offend are to be caſt out of that Church, in caſe they do not reform upon admonition ſeaſonably and frequently given; according to that in Tit. 3. 10 <hi>A man that is an heretick after the firſt and ſecond admonition reject,</hi> caſt him off, ſeparate him from your communion. This Separation is approvable; Thus far you ſee, we may and muſt be Separatiſts, the Holy Ghoſt enjoyneth it, we ſin if we be not ſo; and they that caſt a reproach upon any man for this kind of Separation are in a great fault, and it will be ſin unto them.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:119995:26"/>
            <p> And the Apoſtle in the 2 Cor. Chan. 6. giveth five reaſons to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade to ſuch a Separation as this, when he commandeth to <hi>come out from</hi> ſinners, <hi>and</hi> to <hi>be ſeparate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Becauſe there can be no agreement between the people of God and ſuch ſins and ſinners. This he proveth and confirmeth by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding five Queſtions Verſe 14, 15, 16. The firſt is, <hi>What fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hath righteouſneſs with unrighteouſneſs?</hi> The ſecond, <hi>What com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion hath light with darkneſs?</hi> The third, <hi>What concord hath Chriſt with Belial?</hi> The fourth, <hi>What part hath he that believeth with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidel?</hi> The fifth, <hi>What agreement hath the Temple of God with idols?</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, Theſe things are diametrally contrary the one to the other, they are ſeparated aſunder, and ſo muſt ye be ſeparated from ſin and ſinners.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Becauſe the people of God are the houſe or Temple of God, ver. 16. <hi>For ye are the temple of God.</hi> And it is unmeet that the temple of God ſhould be defiled by having any ſociety with ſin and ſinners; therefore <hi>be ye ſeparate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Becauſe God dwelleth in this temple, ibid. <hi>As God hath ſaid, I will dwell in them and walk in them.</hi> And it is treachery, yea high treaſon to lodg any rebels within or near the habitation of this great King; therefore <hi>ſeparate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Becauſe this God who dwelleth in this temple is the living God, ibid. <hi>Ye are the temple of the living God,</hi> ſo as he taketh notice of our behaviour, and his ſpirit is grieved at this as a great miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage if we hold any communion with ſuch; and therefore we muſt <hi>ſeparate</hi> from them.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Becauſe the people of God are an holy covenant engaged peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, God is their God, and they are his people, ibid. <hi>I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people.</hi> According to that which is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Deut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6. 17, 18. <hi>Thou haſt avouched the Lord this day to be thy God, to walk in his ways, and to keep his ſtatutes, and his commandments and judgments, and to hearken unto his voice. And the Lord hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouched thee this day to be his peculiar people.</hi> And therefore the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God ought warily to avoid and ſeparate from ſuch things or perſons as may endanger a breach of that love and amity that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and them.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:119995:27"/>
            <p> Obſerve then that I ſpeak not againſt all kind of Separation, there is a Separation that is lawfull, holy, and ſtrictly enjoyned us in the word of God.</p>
            <p>Second. Yet there is an unholy, unlawful Separation, an ungodly Separatiſt, condemned in the unerring word of God. You ſee that the Apoſtle Jude condemneth theſe falſe Teachers of whom he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in this Epiſtle for their Separation, amongſt other vices that they were guilty of, and ſets a black mark of infamy upon them, <hi>Theſe be they</hi> (ſaith he, mark, obſerve them well, follow them not) <hi>who ſeparate themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us therefore make enquiry (by the written word of God) who theſe Separatiſts are, that we may know them and avoid them. And I ſhall demonſtrate that in ſix particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Such may juſtly be challenged as guilty of ſinfull Separation, who deline as unlawfull all neceſſary ſociety with them whom they conceive to be unregenerate, ſo as they will not eat or drink or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with them at all. Such were the Phariſees of whom mention is frequently made in the New Teſtament; and they were called Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees from the Hebrew <hi>Pharaſh, ſeparavit.</hi> For though that word be metaphorically expounded to <hi>declare</hi> or to <hi>interprete,</hi> yet proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it ſignifieth to <hi>divide or ſeparate</hi> as the learned obſerve; and ſo the Greeks uſed to call the Phariſees <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Separatiſts; to this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanius agreeth, <hi>Dicebantur Phariſaei, eò quòd ſeparati eſſent ab aliis, propter ſpontaneam ſuperfluam religionem apud ipſos receptam.</hi> Now one main point of their religion lay in this thing, That they refuſed to eat, or drink, or come into the company of any whom they looked upon as ſinners, and blamed all thoſe that followed not their example in this matter, as you find in that ſpeech of theirs to the Diſciples Mat. 9. 11. <hi>Why eateth your Maſter with publicans and ſinners?</hi> But our Lord Jeſus refuſed not to converſe with them upon juſt occaſion as appeareth by his defenſe in the twelfth and thirteenth verſes, <hi>But when Jeſus heard that, he ſaid unto them, They that be whole need not a Phyſician, but they that are ſick. But go ye and learn what that meaneth, I will have mercy and not ſacrifice: for I am not come to call the righteous but ſinners to repentance.</hi> By which anſwer our Lord Jeſus Chriſt doth fully declare unto us that the Phariſees were in a great errour in that point.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119995:27"/>
            <p> And they that practiſe this kind of ſeparation do fail groſsly in two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1 They are an hinderance to the converſion of ſinners, as our Lord ſheweth in the ſcripture now mentioned, if he had not converſed with them a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well as preached publiquely unto them they had never been converted and brought home to God.</p>
            <p n="2">2 They harden ſinners againſt religion and the profeſſors of it by this means; too much auſterity in this kind driveth men into a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of piety and holineſs, who might be won by a more gentle and meek demeanour toward them. Hence it is that the Apoſtle Paul giveth that grave advice to Timothy 1 Tim. 2. 24-26. <hi>The ſervant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle unto all men, apt to teach, patient, in meekneſs inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, if God peradventure will give them repentance to the acknowledging of the truth; and that they may recover themſelves out of the ſnares of the devil, who are taken captive by him at his will.</hi> By what hath been ſaid we ſee that it is ſinfull Separation for a man to refuſe neceſſary company with thoſe who are unregenerate, that it is a great fault and much to be condemned. And therefore the Apoſtle giveth a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table caveat concerning it 1 Cor. 5. 9-11. <hi>I wrote</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>unto you in an epistle not to company with fornicators. Yet not altogether with the fornicators of this world,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But now I have written unto you</hi> (for the explanation of my meaning wherein I was not rightly underſtood) <hi>not to keep company, if any man that is called a brother be a fornicator, or covetous, or an idolater, or a railer, or a drunkard, or an extortioner, with ſuch an one no not to eat.</hi> Where he plainly teacheth, That we ought to eſtrange our ſelves more from ſuch as have made a profeſſion and afterward do fall into ſoul offences, than from ſuch as never did yet come up to ſuch an holy profeſſion of the goſpel. This is the firſt branch of ſinfull Separation.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Thoſe alſo are guilty in this kind that forſake family ſociety upon this pretence, that their relations are unconverted. And I the rather mention this, becauſe it is a great fault of ſome perſons in theſe our days aſwell as in former times. Againſt this practiſe it is that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh expreſly 1 Cor. 7. 10-15. <hi>Let not the wife depart or ſeparate from her huſband</hi> &amp;c. This kind of ſeparation is in it ſelf a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119995:28"/> great ſin, and doth occaſion manifold miſchiefs and inconveniences.</p>
            <p n="3">III. They alſo are to be accounted very faulty in this matter, and have juſtly deſerved the name of Separatiſts, who ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the ſolemn Aſſemblies and Ordinances of Chriſt, and particularly from that great ſealing Ordinance of the Lords ſupper, becauſe there are ſome that communicate with them whom they judg to be unworthy communicants and graceleſs men.</p>
            <p>Before I ſpeak to this point, I muſt lay down and conſtantly affirm theſe two received and well grounded truths, leſt I ſhould be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtood in what I am to ſay.</p>
            <p n="1">1 I ſay, That perſons groſly ignorant, or notoriouſly ungodly and prophane are not fit to receive the Lords Supper, theſe are not able to diſcern the Lords body, but eat and drink unworthily, and ſo are <hi>guilty of the body and bloud-of the Lord,</hi> as the Apoſtle informeth us 1 Gor. 11. 27. 29. Such perſons eat and drink their own damnation.</p>
            <p n="2">2 I affirm, That it is the duty of the Officers of the Church to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from the Lords Supper all ſuch as ſhall appear unto them to be unduly qualified for the receiving of that Ordinance; and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar this belongeth to the Miniſter to <hi>put a difference between holy and unholy, and between unclean and clean,</hi> and accordingly to admit or exclude from ordinances. They were the Prieſts that thruſt Uzziah out of the temple when the leproſie appeared upon him 2. Chr. 26. 19. 20.</p>
            <p>From theſe two undoubted truths which we profeſs, and fear not to practiſe, it is apparent that we allow not promiſcuous or mixt communion; but that it is a falſe report and ſlander that the devil and the ſectaries have caſt upon us to advance their own intereſt thereby. And (if it were lawful to boaſt) we may ſay that our Ordinances are kept as pure from mixt communion as theirs are, bleſſed be God.</p>
            <p>Yet (though all this be true) it muſt be conſtantly received and maintained as a great truth, That private Chriſtians may not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeparate themſelves from the Church, or decline any of Chriſts Ordinances, becauſe they ſee ſome perſons admitted to participate with them in thoſe Ordinances whom themſelves look upon as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men; and That it is a foul fault thus to ſeparate. There were great diſorders in the Church of Corinth in thoſe perſons who came unto the Table of the Lord 1. Cor. 11. 21, 22. one came to it <hi>hungry</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:119995:28"/> and <hi>another drunken</hi> (greater miſcarriages then are to be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our communicants when they come to the Sacrament) and the Apoſtle chideth them ſharply about thoſe things, <hi>What</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>have ye not houſes to eat and to drink in? or deſpiſe ye the Church of God, and ſhame them that have not? What ſhall I ſay to you? ſhall I praiſe you in this? I praiſe you not.</hi> Their diſorder called aloud for reformation, and the Apoſtle took a great deal of pains to reform it, by reducing them to the firſt inſtitution. But you find not that he gives any commandment or allowance to any of the members of that Church to withdraw themſelves and ſeparate from communion in that Ordinance with the Church. No, he commends them for this that they who were godly did not ſeparate but came ſtill <hi>together into one place,</hi> Verſe 20; and he ſharply reproveth their ſchiſms and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions Chap. 3. 3. And there is great reaſon why Chriſtians ſhould be very cautious in this caſe. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Such perſons who may by a private Chriſtian or Chriſtians be judged to be unworthy to participate in that Ordinance, may yet be worthy, and ſo accounted of in the judgment of thoſe that are Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Church; whoſe judgment is to be preferred before any private opinion of the beſt men. It may be ſaid of a private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in this caſe as the Hebrew ſaid to Moſes Acts 7. 27. <hi>Who made thee a ruler and a judg?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Though the perſons be indeed unworthy, yet their unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may be unknown unto the Officers of the Church. And it is the duty of private Chriſtians to make known ſuch offenders to thoſe that are over them in the Lord, that ſo their reformation may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured, and not therefore to decline and ſeparate from the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. This is the ſtanding rule, <hi>Dic eccleſiae</hi> Mat. 18. 17. He ſaith not, If thou be offended fall off from the Church, but acquaint the Church, that ſo the ſcandal in thy way may be removed.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thoſe that rule in the Church may ſuſpect that ſuch or ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are unworthy, and yet there can be no full proof made of it. The opinion or knowledg of one private Chriſtian may not be a ſufficient proof in ſome caſes, but there muſt be two or three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. And where full proof is wanting, there can be no warrant for a judicial proceeding, nor ſufficient ground to account ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119995:29"/> or perſons unworthy of that Ordinance. Charity will ſurmiſe no evil without ſufficient proof made. When Paul was <hi>coming the third time</hi> to Corinth to reform their diſorder in the Ordinances of Chriſt, he telleth them what courſe he would follow in that work 2 Cor. 13. 1. <hi>In the mouth of two or three witneſſes ſhall every word be eſtabliſhed;</hi> he would not take upon him to judg by hear-ſay and bare reports, but by full and clear proof; which ought to be laid down as a pattern in all Church cenſures.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Although it fall out ſo that full proof may be had of a fault committed by a Church-member, and that the Officers of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation may be fully perſuaded, that that perſon hath done ſuch a thing as might juſtly exclude him from the Lotds table, if he do not repent of it; yet it may be there hath not been an opportunity as yet to hear the witneſſes, and to deal with him by private Admonition, whereupon repentance may follow ſo evidently that there may be no occaſion to proceed to ſuſpenſion; much leſs can there then be an occaſion for a private Chriſtian to withdraw communion in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances upon that account. It were (as I conceive) prepoſterous and againſt the rule, to ſuſpend any Church-member from the ſealing Ordinances before he be admoniſhed of his fault, and have ſhewed his obſtinacie. Or it may be that ſuch a mans repentance aſwell as his fault is ſufficiently known to the Governors of the Church, though not to every private member, and if his repentance be known to them, and they be ſatisfied therewith, that ſhould give much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to others in diverſe caſes. Paul ſuppoſed that his teſtimony of the repentance of Oneſimus was a ſufficient ground of ſatisfaction to Philemon, as is evident in the epiſtle to Philemon.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Admit that the fault be notorious, and evidently proved, and that thoſe who are in authority in the Church do ſinfully connive at it, and caſt not out the offender according to his merit; (as it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to have been in the church of <hi>Corinth)</hi> yet that is no ſound ground to forſake communion with that church. No private chriſtian needs to fear that he ſhall be acceſſory to that mans ſin, or receive hurt by participation in that Ordinance whereunto the other is admitted. No, it is the fault of children to refuſe the bread which their father offereth to them, becauſe dogs are ſuffered to be in the room and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119995:29"/> ſnatch at the childrens portion, there would appear more of ſurli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs than of diſcretion and godly wiſdom in that. The Apoſtles or ſome of them at leaſt did participate with Judas in a ſealing Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance after he was detected to be the traitor, as appeareth by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring John 13. 23-27. with Mat. 26. 23-26.</p>
            <p>This rejection of Ordinances, this ſeparation from them, upon ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition that unworthy perſons are admitted, is to be ſeverely cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured as proud cenſoriouſneſs, and uncharitable raſhneſs, which God abhorreth, notwithſtanding that pretence of piety that is put upon it. Theſe are they that ſay, <hi>Stand by thy ſelf and come not near</hi> us, <hi>for</hi> we are <hi>bolier than thou.</hi> But mark what a character the Lord giveth of them Iſa 65. 5. <hi>Theſe are a ſmoak in my noſe,</hi> they are a greater offenſe to God, than the ſtinking ſnuff of a candle can be to any of us. It becometh true Chriſtians to judg themſelves and to ſuſpect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves rather than other men, and to ſweep at their own dores firſt. Our Lord giveth excellent advice to us all Mat. 7. 1, 2. <hi>Judg not that ye be not judged: for with what judgment ye judg, ye ſhall be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and with what meaſure ye mete it ſhall be meaſured to you again.</hi> It comes to paſs frequently, that the weakeſt Chriſtians are moſt cenſorious, and thoſe that are ſtrongeſt are moſt charitable.</p>
            <p>I ſay not but that it is the part of a godly man to mourn if he ſee thoſe that are unworthy perſons admitted to ſealing Ordinances; but he may not therefore ſeparate from thoſe Ordinances whilſt they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main Gods Ordinances. This is an occaſion of much hurt and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief in the church of God, and it were more ſafe for Chriſtians to keep themſelves within their due bounds and limits. It was the ſin of the people to <hi>abhor the offering of the Lord,</hi> 1 Sam. 2. 17. although thoſe that did officiate therein were very lewd men. That is the third branch of ſinful ſeparation.</p>
            <p n="4">IIII Thoſe are alſo in a great meaſure guilty of hateful Separation that decline private chriſtian communion with the godly in ſuch du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as are of common concernment to all that fear God, <hi>as prayer, reading the word, conference</hi> &amp;c. <hi>They that feared God ſpake often one to another,</hi> Mal. 3. 16.</p>
            <p>Yet even herein there is ſingular caution to be uſed. For when ſuch private meetings are made the anvil whereon to hammer out treaſon,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119995:30"/> and ſedition in the land, and the ſnare and bait to draw men into ſeparation from our publique Congregations, then (whatſoever glorious gloſs may be put upon them) they ceaſe to be ſuch meetings wherein Chriſt will be preſent; ſuch aſſemblies every good foul ought to withdraw from, and they ought to be ſuppreſted by the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Magiſtrate. Such ſeditious meetings I am ſure have many of thoſe been of late years which have been ſaid to be religious, and in them many of our late miſeries have been firſt plotted and contrived.</p>
            <p>But when Gods people do meet onely for edification, and to build up themſelves in their moſt holy faith with prayer in the holy Ghoſt, and do not intermeddle to the diſadvantage of Church or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, but pray for and ſeek the general good of both (as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God did in theſe nations forty and fifty years ago,) then ſuch meetings are to be countenanced and frequented. And for want of this holy private communion of Saints it cometh to paſs that beleev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers loſe much comfort, cool in their love to God and his people, and ruſt in their graces much more then formerly. From this private Chriſtian communion we muſt not ſeparate.</p>
            <p n="5">V They that ſeparate from the church of Chriſt from that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular congregation whereof they are members, for ſome errour which they conceive to be therein, and gather themſelves into other ſocieties diſtinct therefrom, are without doubt guilty of ſinful Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in an high degree. It is no light thing to give a bill of divorce to the Spouſe of Chriſt to count her for an harlot in whoſe womb we have been conceived, who hath brought us forth for God, and nouriſhed us till we were brought up, and all becauſe ſhe hath ſome ſpots and blemiſhes upon her. This courſe is againſt the Law of the divine nature, and repugnant to the modeſty of a Saint like profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. True born children will rather endeavour to wipe off the ſtains that are upon their mothers face, and lay a garment upon their ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and go backward, and cover her nakedneſs. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt would not caſt off the church of the Jews, though there was abundance of corruption therein, but held her as a true church, and ſo did the Apoſtles likewiſe. God doth and will bear much more with us before he will caſt us off, he never giveth a bill of divorce to any church till ſhe firſt leave him; And we ſhould be like unto our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119995:30"/> Father. Thoſe perſons who take this courſe, to unchurch the church of Chriſt, do proclaim openly to the world that they are ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards, and not ſons. That is the fifth branch of unholy Separation.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Laſtly. They alſo are guilty of this fault that ſeparate to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane devices in the worſhip and ſervice of God, though yet they hold communion with the true church. There are many that live in the church, of whom alſo we have cauſe to hope that they are true members and dear to God, and yet they fail herein, are apt to make mixtures of their own in Gods worſhip. Hence it is that the Lord giveth ſuch a ſtrict charge to the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Deut. 12. 32. and elſe where. <hi>What thing ſoever I command thee thou ſhalt obſerve to do, thou ſhalt neither ad to it nor diminiſh from it.</hi> Such were the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees of whom I ſpake even now, they ſet up their own waſhings and puriſyings together with rhoſe that were appointed in the Law of the Lord, and put more ſanctity and holineſs in them then in the Lords own inſtitutions. Of this the Evangeliſt ſpeaketh Mar. 7 3 4. <hi>The Phariſees and all the Jews, except they waſh their hands oft, eat not, holding the traditions of the Elders. And when they come from the market except they waſh they eat not, And many other things there be which they have received to hold, as the waſhing of cups and pots, braſen veſſels and of tables.</hi> But our Saviour chargeth them with ſeparation for it Verſe 7. 8. <hi>In vain do they worſhip me teaching for doctrines the commandments of men, for laying aſide the commandment of God ye hold the traditions of men.</hi> And Verſe 10. <hi>Ye reject the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of God that ye may keep your own traditions.</hi> When the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies and devices of men in any kind are impoſed, or received into the worſhip of God, ſo far God is ſlighted, his worſhip defiled, and a rent made in the Church of God.</p>
            <p>Thus have we ſeen that there is an unholy and unlawful Separation, and what it is. And from theſe qualifications of the Doctrine, it now appeareth more fully and evidently, That there is a ſeparation that hath been an old errour in ſome men that have pretended to be knowing and religious, even teachers in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There needs not to be much time ſpent in further proof of this point, you may be pleaſed to obſerve theſe few particulars briefly.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Out own experience doth ſufficiently inform us of the truth of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119995:31"/> this point, there is at this day a grievous Separation made from the church, the bitterneſs of this cup we have taſted in the three nations, we find it to have infected many Cities, Towns, and Families.</p>
            <p n="2">2 We have alſo ſufficient teſtimony of the antiquity of this abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; it is not a brat of yeſterdayes breeding, but it is an old errour wherewith many profeſſours have been defiled. Let us look backward a little, and take notice of its Pedegree.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as the children of Iſrael were ſettled in a church ſtate by <hi>Moſes</hi> in the wilderneſs, we find that <hi>Korah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> began this Separation, of whom we read in the ſixteenth Chapter of the book of Numbers, They were men famous in the Congregation, and <hi>Korah</hi> was a Levite alſo; you may likewiſe obſerve there, what a wonderful fair pretence of holineſs they put on for the carrying on of their ſchiſme, and rebellion, to the intent that they might draw the people after them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gideon</hi> was an holy and good man, yet he alſo made a rent in the church of God, inſomuch as <hi>all Iſrael</hi> in a manner <hi>went a whoring after the Ephod which he had made and put in his city</hi> Ophrah Judg. 8. 27.</p>
            <p>What a ſchiſme, rene, and ſeparation did <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the ſon of <hi>Nebat</hi> make from the church of God when he drew the ten tribes to idolatry? and yet he covereth it with a fair pretence of reaſon and piety alſo, as is to be ſeen at large 1 King. Chap. 12.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> informeth us that the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were guilty of Separation and diviſions 1 Cor. 3. 3; one would be of <hi>Pauls</hi> church, another of <hi>Apolloes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> another of <hi>Cephas</hi> his church, ſo that they were broken into diverſe parties and factions, and yet they were very wiſe men, and pretended to very much holineſs alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jude</hi> that out lived him, is not ſilent concerning the ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made in his days by thoſe that pretended to be teachers in the church of God, as you have heard already cleared out of the Text.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pelagians, Donatiſts, Familiſts</hi> and all the old hereticks in the church for diverſe hundred years after Chriſt, were many of them learned men and laid claim to much ſanctity and holineſs yet you know what ſad rents and ſeparations they made in the church of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119995:31"/>
            <p> The Antichriſt of Rome hath made as great a pretence to holineſs as any other; and yet you cannot be ignorant that the ſchiſme, and ſeparation he hath made in the church of God hath been to great, that for diverſe hundreds of years ſcarce ſo much as the face of a church appeared in theſe Weſternly parts of the world ſave in ſome few holes and corners.</p>
            <p>When God was pleaſed to diſpell the darkneſs of popery in the dayes of <hi>Luiher,</hi> and that the church of God began to flouriſh in <hi>Germany,</hi> behold on a ſudden there ariſeth a deadly Separation made by the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> and their Aſſociates in thoſe parts, and all was under the diſguiſe of inſpirations and revelations from God.</p>
            <p>And Laſtly, When the work of reformation began to be ſet on foot among us in theſe nations about the year one thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and forty, and the minds of the good people of the Lands were much comforted in hope of unity, and uniformity in the worſhip of God in theſe Lands, be hold what a Separation and Schiſme hath been made to the retarding of that glorious work, inſomuch as the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the temple of God hath ceaſed for diverſe years elapſed, and yet this hath been done under the pretence of holineſs and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the intereſt of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. I need ſay no more for proof.</p>
            <p>Let us now proceed to the uſes of the Doctrine, which are three, 1 Of Inquiſition. 2 Of Humiliation. 3 Of Exhortation.</p>
            <p>Uſe 1. Of inquiſition or enquiry, Whether there be any of theſe ſinfull Separatiſts among us in this Common wealth, or no? But this is ſo obvious that it is written with a Sun beam. Have not we mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes among us that have departed from our ſolemn Aſſemblies, and caſt off the publique Ordinances of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the ſealing Ordinances upon a meer pretence of non-commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the ungodly? Nay have we not very many, both Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and others that have caſt off our Churches, and en bodied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into other ſocieties? None can deny this, he is blind that ſeeth it not.</p>
            <p>Now let us yet enquire further. What is the reaſon why they have ſo done? They muſt either acknowledg our Congregations to be true Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, or elſe they muſt ſay that we are falſe Churches. <hi>Non datur tertium.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:119995:32"/>
            <p> If they acknowledg us to be true Churches (as ſome of them do) then why do they ſeparate from us? They cannot be excuſed from the guilt of Schiſm at the leaſt. And do they not put themſelves out of Chriſts protection by their ſeparation? Yea verily, and they will feel it to be ſo at the laſt. If they endeavour to excuſe the matter thus, That though we be true Churches, yet we are not pure Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and they deſire to gather into a more pure Church way, and therefore are not to be accuſed for unlawfull Separation. I muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in four words.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That they have no precept or example in the whole Book of God, for going out of a true Church upon pretence of greater purity to be found in another, and <hi>whatſoever is not of faith is ſin</hi> Rom. 14. 23.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That we have the example of Chriſt to the contrary who would not ſeparate from the Church of the Jews though corrupted, and gather another from among them of a more pure conſtitution, whilſt they were to remain a Church; and they ought to be <hi>followers of God a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dear children,</hi> Eph. 5. 1.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That this ſeparation (though under the pretence of greater pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to be found elſe where) is a dangerous ſign that they were never true members of the church. I would not judge them, but let us hear what the Holy Ghoſt ſaith by the Apoſtle 1 Joh. 2. 19. <hi>They went out from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would no doubt have continued with us; but they went out that they might be made manifest, that they were not all of us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 This departure of theirs is an occaſion of very grievous diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity and diſadvantage to the church of God in general, which they ought warily to have declined; inſomuch as the bleſſed work of reformation is retarded by their means; and our Saviour ſaith Mat. 18. 7. <hi>We to that man by whom the offence cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If (on the other ſide) they ſhall ſay we are not true churches of Chriſt, and that therefore they leave us; then (behold) we have (bleſſed be God) all the marks and ſignes of a true church. We ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the true and incorruptible doctrine of the Prophets, and Apoſtles, and receive it as the onely rule for faith and manners; We have a continuation of the right and lawful uſe of the Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119995:32"/> among us; and (which is the thing that themſelves make the moſt eſſential note of a church truely inſtituted.) We have the ſound and ſincere <hi>profeſſion of the true faith</hi> among us. So as they can have no cauſe to judg otherwiſe then that we are the true church of God.</p>
            <p>What then is the cauſe that ſhould make them to ſeparate from us? Surely the fault lieth not in us becauſe we are not the church of God, but there is ſomething in themſelves that is amiſs it will fall under one of theſe three cauſes, I will not determine which of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Either, They are proud and high minded men, that ſet more price, and eſteem upon their own abilities, parts, and graces then upon their brethrens. This is indeed the ſeed of Separation, when a man is puffed up with pride of ſpirit. This was the fault of thoſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nted diviſion in the church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> they had an high conceit of themſelves, and <hi>commended themſelves</hi> and then own abilities as the Apoſtle intimateth 2 Cor. 10. 18. but they had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe thoughts and uttered unſit ſpeeches againſt <hi>Paul</hi> Verſe 10. <hi>His bodily preſence</hi> (ſay they) <hi>is weak, and his ſpeech contemptible;</hi> he had no good elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. But this is far off from that which Chriſt requireth to be in his diſciples, the firſt leſſon to be learned in his ſchool is <hi>ſelf deniall</hi> Mat. 16. 24. <hi>If any man will come after me, let him deny himſelf.</hi> A low eſteem of ſelf, would keep a man ſafe from being a Separatiſt; but when pride thus pricketh a man forward, and that he valueth his own wiſdom, and learning at a higher rate then the wiſdom, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and holineſs of a whole national Aſſembly of Orthodox Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines it is no wonder though he run upon this dangerous rock of ſeparation.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or elſe, Self ends and baſe carnal reſpects draw men into this gulf; they aim at their own advantage and ſelf intereſt, to make themſelves great and rich in the world. The Apoſtle ſpeaketh fully to this 2 Pet. 2. 1-3. where he informeth us that falſe teachers <hi>through cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs do with fained words make merchandiſe</hi> of profeſſors. Such kind of trading as is there ſpoken of is baſe among men, and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in the ſight of God. Hope of great gifts and large rewards maketh many a man to turn Separatiſt. Or if they aim not at an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eſtate, yet at leaſt a great name, fame and honor among men
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119995:33"/> doth entice them to this vanity. This was it that tickled the new fangled preachers at Epheſus Acts 20. 30. <hi>They ſhall ſpeak perverſe things to draw away diſciples after them;</hi> they thought they ſhould have a great company of followers if they ſet up new faſhions in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and diſcipline. And have not ſome of the Separatiſts enlarged their precincts beyond the bounds of a Lord Biſhops dioceſs, they are likely to watch well one over another living at ſuch a diſtance. Theſe are <hi>they</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) that <hi>ſeek honour one of another, and ſeek not the honour that cometh of God onely</hi> Joh. 5. 44.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Or elſe, they warp to ſeparation through their own injudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs being unſetled in the knowledg of the truth. It is for want of ſound catechiſing in the fundamentals of religion that ſo many have of late been troubled with this vertigo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they have got more uſe of their tongues than Chriſtians had formerly, but they have leſs in their hearts than the old Chriſtians had. If men were well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in religion they would not be ſo eaſily ſeduced to ſeparation. The cauſe why men are deceived by ſuch <hi>deluſions, is becauſe they have not received the love of the truth</hi> into their ſouls 2 Theſ. 2. 10, 11. They cannot by found judgment diſcern between truth and error when a falſe teacher cometh in appearance as if he were an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of light; this want of judgment perverteth thouſands.</p>
            <p>Uſe 2. Hence there ariſeth juſt ground of humiliation before the Lord this day, in that this error of ſeparation from the Church of Chriſt is ſo overſpred theſe dominions, and over this iſland particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly. I told you in the begining of my diſcourſe that this is the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chan, the Peſt of our lands, and that I would clear that unto you; which I ſhall now do (but with much brevity) that ſo our hearts may be the more deeply humbled in the preſence of God. The abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of this ſin of ſeparating from the Church and Ordinances of Chriſt will appear in theſe four particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Separation is the moſt fruitfull ſin of many others, it is a very comprehenſive evil, the womb out of which iſſues many prodigious monſters. If I ſhould begin to ſhew its riſe and growth it may be it would prove offenſive to ſome here preſent, and it would be beſide my purpoſe. Obſerve (therefore) onely its of spring; hence ariſe many of the hereſies and abominations that are how among us; we
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119995:33"/> are peſtered with Anabaptiſts, Seekers, Quakers, and the like ſorts of vipers, but they all began in Separation. Men firſt run out of the Church and then they may be of any religion they pleaſe. Our late experience doth abundantly confirm this. And how indeed ſhould it be otherwiſe, when men forſake the true Church, what hindreth but they may erect any Church that they ſhall deviſe. The fruitfulneſs of it maketh it the fouler ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Separation is a ſin that many of Gods own people (as we do conceive in the judgment of charity) are ſmutted and tainted with. And the ſins of Gods children are aggravated by many more circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances than the ſins of other men are. <hi>Iſrael hath ſinned</hi> was that which God affirmeth to Joſhua as a great ground of humiliation, Chap. 7. 11. The children of God ſin againſt greater outward light and means of grace than others do, they ſin againſt the inward light of the ſpirit of God, they ſin againſt greater mercies than others do, they ſin againſt covenants, vows, and ſtrong reſolutions. This makes their ſin of ſeparation much the greater, and more to be lamented in the preſence of God, it is the ſin his own people.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Separation is a greater ſin by far than otherwiſe it would be, in this reſpect, becauſe it is maintained, countenanced and preached up as if it were no ſin at all but a duty. This kind withdrawing from Church and Ordinances is held forth as a great goſpel truth by many. Satans temptation was the more dangerous, and the womans tranſgreſſion the greater, when the forbidden fruit was eaten of under the ſhew and appearance of <hi>good</hi> Gen. 3. 5, 6. It is a great ſin to call that good that is evil in it ſelf. God cannot abide it when men are ſo ſtupid as to call darkneſs light. This alſo calleth for mourning.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Separation is that leaven which leaveneth the whole lump, it is that canker or gangren that will (if God prevent it not) eat out the heart of all goodneſs, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of the doctrine of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meneus and Philetus 2 Tim. 2. 17. It is indeed a dangerous ſign of a carnal man, though he may be cloathed in a religious habit. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle propoundeth this queſtion to thoſe that ſtudied to make a rent at Corinth, and to thoſe that were led by them 1 Cor. 3. 3, 4. <hi>Are ye not carnal?</hi> As if he had ſaid, I much ſuſpect your grace, and doubt that you are perſons carnal, ſenſual, having not the ſpirit, becauſe ye
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119995:34"/> run thus into ſeparations and diviſions in the Church. We have now done with the ſecond uſe.</p>
            <p>Uſe 3. If ſeparation be ſuch an old, dangerous, ſpreading and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taminating evil, then here is exhortation in two branches,</p>
            <p n="1">I. If this be ſo great an evil, then (I beg) that you flie ſeparation, and alſo thoſe that would entice you to it, take heed of being drawn from that Church in which you have been born and brought up for God. <hi>Meddle you not with them that are given to change</hi> their Church, It becometh us all to be of Davids mind who profeſſeth Pſal. 119. 113. <hi>I hate vain thoughts.</hi> It is in the original more emphatical <hi>ramos,</hi> or <hi>ſummitates arborum.</hi> I hate to be like the upper branches of a tree that are bowed and ſhaken with every wind, to be a weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock in religion, without ballaſt, changing and turning with every turn of the times. O this is an hateful thing indeed.</p>
            <p>Now if you would be preſerved from this evil, that you may not be ſeduced into ſeparation, I ſhal preſcribe unto you five helps, which are all laid down by the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> in the two verſes that do ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed our Text <hi>(viz.)</hi> Verſe 20. 21. <hi>But ye beloved, building up your ſelves on your most holy faith, praying in the holy Ghost, keep your ſelves in the love of God, looking for the mercy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt unto eternal life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 He that would be kept from ſeparation muſt lay a good founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of faith in his heart. This is cleerly hinted in theſe words. <hi>Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up your ſelves in your moſt holy faith;</hi> there muſt firſt be a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion laid before we can rear a building<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Faith is this foundation to build upon, <hi>building on your faith.</hi> Faith in Chriſt Jeſus will keep a man from ſeduction. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this rock</hi> (ſaith our Savour Mat. 16 18. <hi>viz.</hi> upon my ſelf whom thou haſt now confeſſed.) <hi>I will build my church, and the gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt it,</hi> neither Satan nor ſeducers ſhall be able to lead him from the church who hath true faith fixed upon Chriſt, faith will conquer.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When you have digged deep and are come to the foundation you muſt build upon it unto perfection. <hi>Building up your ſelves on your moſt holy faith.</hi> He that would ſtand againſt wind and weather and not be ſhaken and rent from the church, muſt be ſure to build upon the foundation, and upon that onely. If a man build partly upon the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119995:34"/> foundation, and partly beſide it, his building will ſettle and fall; or if a man leave earth and rubiſh between the foundation and the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the fabrick will come to naught. The cauſe why the houſe ſtood <hi>when the rain deſcended, and the flouds came, and the windes blew and beat upon it,</hi> was becauſe <hi>it was founded upon a rock,</hi> Mat. 7. 24. 25. On the otherſide, The cauſe why the other houſe ſtood not but fell when <hi>the rain deſcended, and the flouds came, and the winds blew and beat upon it</hi> was becauſe <hi>it was built upon the ſand,</hi> and not upon the foundation. Verſe 26. 27. The more that a man laboureth for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of faith, to be made compleat in Chriſt, the more ſhall he be kept from being a Separatiſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3 You muſt pray fervently for your perfeverance in church-ſtate, and fellowſhip. <hi>Praying in the holy Ghost;</hi> that is, in the ſtrength of the ſpirit of God, by his motion and inſpiration, and not with the mouth onely as hypocrites uſe to do; it is not lip labour that will ſerve the turn, but prayer with the ſpirit, will keep a man from this errour. There is a promiſe which may be extended thus far, Act. 2. 21. <hi>It ſhall come to paſs that whoſoever ſhall call upon the name of the Lord ſhall be ſaved,</hi> not onely from everlaſting ruine, but from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking, and departing from the true church. Prayer is a notable help in this thing.</p>
            <p n="4">4 He that would be preſerved from this evil muſt love God, and his truth. <hi>Keep your ſelves in the love of God.</hi> He that buildeth upon the foundation, and prayeth much ſhall be ſo kept in the love of God, and of his church and people, that he ſhall not fall off to Separation.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Hope of heaven muſt be firmly rooted in the heart of him that would decline this ſinful Separation, <hi>Looking for the mercy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt unto eternal life.</hi> Hope of eternal glory will make a man carefully to avoid thoſe allurements that may draw him into this diſorder, and ſo obſtruct his expectation of that everlaſting reſt, whereof his abiding in the church of God upon earth is a ſigne or ſymbole. So much for the firſt exhortation.</p>
            <p n="2">II If Separation be fo old, and dangerous an errour, and have ſo overſpread this Commonwealth, Then labour (I pray you) to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thoſe who are ſeduced into this errour. This is a great act of charity to recover a falne Chriſtian from the errour of his way.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:119995:35"/>
            <p> How this is to be done is alſo declared by this our Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> in the two and twentieth and three and twentieth verſes of this Epiſtle <hi>And of ſome have compaſſion making a difference: And others ſave with fear pulling them out of the fire.</hi> Where we are to obſerve, That we muſt not deal with all men alike in reducing them to ſoundneſs in the faith, but we muſt <hi>put a difference</hi> in our dealing with them. Where the Apoſtle ſeemeth to allude to the Lords direction given under the Law concerning the purifying of things taken or recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in war, Num. 31. 23. <hi>Every thing that may abide the fire ye ſhall make it go through the fire, and it ſhall be clean; nevertheleſs it ſhall be purifyed with the water of Separation: and all that abideth not the fire ye ſhall make it go through the water.</hi> They were to deal in their purification as the nature of the thing to be purified did require. If that they took any prey that would abide the fire as gold, ſilver, braſs, iron, tinne, or lead, that was to be purifyed by fire; but that which was combuſtible and would be conſumed if put into the fire, muſt be purifyed by water onely. So here, in reducing a ſeduced brother fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into an errour, he adviſeth to diſtinguiſh of men, to make a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the temper of their ſpirits and to deal with them accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly in this caſe. For that ſeverity that may be profitable to one man, may prove very unprofitable and deſtructive to another, and that gentleneſs that may recover one man may leave another ſtill in his errour. And therefore he adviſeth in both theſe things that which may be worth our conſideration and practiſe in theſe times of ſeduction and ſeparation.</p>
            <p n="1">1 He directeth that of ſome we have compaſſion. Thoſe perſons who are of a meek and tractible frame of ſpirit ſhould be handled gently and tenderly although they have erred. Meek and humble ſpirits will ſoon be oppreſſed if any violence be offered to them. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh notably to this point, Gal. 6. 1. <hi>Brethren if any man be overtaken in a fault ye which are ſpiritual reſtore ſuch an one in the ſpirit of meekneſs, conſidering thy ſelf leſt thou alſo be tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Where obſerve. 1 Of whom he ſpeaketh ſuch as were fallen through infirmity onely and not wilfully which he calleth an <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking in a fault,</hi> fallen into an errour inconſiderately. 2 What is
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119995:35"/> to be done in this caſe. <hi>Restore ſuch a one in the ſpirit of meekneſs</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Reſtore or ſet him in joint again,</hi> The phraſe is bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from Chirurgions, who being to deal with a broken joint will handle the ſame very tenderly: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o tender muſt we be in deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with thoſe that erre through infirmity. 3 The reaſon the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle giveth, <hi>Conſidering thy ſelf leſt thou alſo be tempted.</hi> Every man, the beſt Chriſtian is ſubject to errour; therefore be tender and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate to ſuch as are not ſullen, wilful, and reſolute, but have ſlipped onely through inadvertancy and common frailty. This is the courſe to be taken with meek and humble ſouls that erre.</p>
            <p n="2">2 He adviſeth, That thoſe which are ſtuborn, obſtinate, and contumacious ſhould be more roughly handled, with greater and more earneſt expreſſion of deteſtation to their errours. <hi>And others ſave with fear</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>pulling them out of the fire.</hi> Snatch them out of the danger as firebrands out of the fire; or as the angel did <hi>Lot</hi> and his wife, and daughters out of <hi>Sodom</hi> when they lingred and put off, Gen. 19. 16.</p>
            <p>It will be a ſingular point of prudence and piety in you who are members of this Honourable Convention, and in all Magiſtrates, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and private Chriſtians to learn to put this difference, that ſo you may carry it aright toward them that are fallen into this ſinfull Separation. The Lord be pleaſed out of his great mercy to teach us all this leſſon. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:119995:36"/>
            <head>
               <hi>March</hi> the 9. 1659.</head>
            <head type="sub">By the General Convention of Ireland.</head>
            <p>ORdered, That Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Doctor <hi>Jones,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Hill</hi> be and are hereby appointed a Committee to return the thanks of this Convention to Mr. <hi>Coxe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Charnock,</hi> Mr. <hi>Adare</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bains</hi> for their pains in carrying on the work of this day in <hi>Chriſt-Church Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin;</hi> And that Mr. <hi>Coxe,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nock</hi> be deſired to print their reſpective Sermons this day by them delivered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Convention.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Signed by Order, Ma. Barry</hi> Clerk of the General Convention of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:119995:36"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Imprinted by WILLIAM BLADEN, <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
